<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="advanced.topics.adding.vmware.esxi.host">


    <title>Inventorying vCenter/vSphere ESXi Hosts with SUSE Manager</title>
    <sect1>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>With the release of SUSE Manager 3, foreign virtual hosts (e.g. vCenter and vSphere
            ESXi) may be inventoried using the <filename>Virtual Host Manager</filename>. From the
            vSphere Client you can define roles and permissions for vCenter /vSphere ESXi users
            allowing vSphere objects and resources to be imported and inventoried by SUSE Manager.
            Objects and resources are then displayed as foreign hosts on the SUSE Manager <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Systems</guimenu>
                <guimenu>Virtual Systems</guimenu>
            </menuchoice> page.</para>
        <para>The following sections will guide you through: </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Requirements</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Overview of permissions and roles</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Adding vCenter and vSphere ESXi hosts to SUSE Manager</para>
            </listitem>
            <!--  <listitem>
                <para>Bootstrapping supported ESXi hosts, (e.g. SLES and RES) for management via
                    Salt</para>
            </listitem>-->
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <para>The following table displays the default API communication port and required access
            rights for inventorying objects and resources.</para>
        <informaltable>
            <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="1*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="1*"/>
                <thead>
                    <row>
                        <entry><para>Ports / Permissions</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>Description</para></entry>
                    </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                    <row>
                        <entry><para>443</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>Default port that SUSE Manager uses to access the ESXi API for
                                obtaining infrastructure data</para></entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <entry><para>read-only</para></entry>
                        <entry><para>All vCenter/ESXi objects and resources that should be inventoried by the Virtual Host Manager
                                should be at least assigned the <emphasis>read-only</emphasis> role.
                                Mark objects and resources with <emphasis>no-access</emphasis> to
                                exclude them from the inventory.</para></entry>
                    </row>
                </tbody>
            </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Permissions and Roles Overview</title>
        <para>The following section will guide you through assigning user permissions and roles in
            vCenter/ESXi.</para>
        <para>A user is someone who has been authorized access to an ESXi host. The Virtual Host
            Manager (located on the SUSE Manager server) will inventory ESXi data defined by
            assigned roles and permissions on a user account. </para>
        <para>For example: The user John has been assigned the <emphasis>read-only</emphasis> access
            role to all servers and datacenters in his company with one exception. Johns account has
            been assigned the <emphasis>no-access</emphasis> role on the company's
                <emphasis>Financial Database server </emphasis>. You decide to use Johns user
            account and add the ESXi host to SUSE Manager. During the inventory the<emphasis>
                Financial Database server</emphasis> will be excluded.</para>
        <para>Keep user access roles in mind when planning to add ESXi hosts to SUSE manager. It is
            important to understand that SUSE Manager will not inventory any objects or resources
            assigned with the no-access role on any user account.</para>
        <tip>
            <title>User Roles/Permissions</title>
            <para>When planning to add new ESXi hosts to SUSE Manager, ask yourself the following
                question:</para>
            <para><emphasis>Have users assigned to a host been provided with the required roles and
                    permissions for objects and resources that should be inventoried by SUSE
                    Manager?</emphasis></para>
        </tip>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Adding New Users and Assigning Roles</title>
        <para>See the official vSphere documentation on adding new users and assigning roles.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para><link
                        xlink:href="https://pubs.vmware.com/vsphere-50/index.jsp#com.vmware.vsphere.security.doc_50/GUID-D7AEC653-EBC8-4573-B990-D8E58742F8ED.html"
                        >Authentication and User Management</link></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Inventorying vCenter/vSphere ESXi Hosts</title>
        <para>The following procedure will guide you through inventorying a VSphere ESXi host with
            &susemgr;.</para>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>From the &susemgr; &webui; select <guimenu>Systems</guimenu> and then
                        <guimenu>Virtual Host Managers</guimenu> from the left navigation bar.
                </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>From the upper right corner of the <guimenu>Virtual Host Managers</guimenu>
                    page select <guimenu>Add VMware-based Virtual Host Manager</guimenu>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>From the <guimenu>Add a VMware-based Virtual Host Manager</guimenu> page fill
                    the following fields with your ESXi host data:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Label: Custom name for your Virtual Host Manager</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Hostname: FQDN or host IP address</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Port: Default ESXi API port</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Username: ESXi user</para>
                        <important>
                            <para>Remember that only objects and resources which match a users
                                defined role will be inventoried. Set the users role on objects and
                                resources you want inventoried to
                                <emphasis>read-only</emphasis></para>
                        </important>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Password: ESXi users password</para>
                    </listitem>

                </itemizedlist>
                <informalfigure>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject role="fo">
                            <imagedata fileref="systems_virtual_host_managers_vmware.png" width="444"/>
                        </imageobject>
                        <imageobject role="html">
                            <imagedata fileref="systems_virtual_host_managers_vmware.png" width="80%"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </informalfigure>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Click the <guimenu>Add Virtual Host Manager</guimenu> button.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>From the <guimenu>Virtual Host Managers</guimenu> page select the newly added
                    Virtual Host manager.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>From the Virtual Host Managers <guimenu>Properties</guimenu> page select
                        <guimenu>Refresh data from this Virtual Host Manager.</guimenu></para>
                <important>
                    <para>If you do not refresh the data from a new Virtual Host Manager, host data
                        will not be inventoried and therefore will not be displayed under <menuchoice>
                            <guimenu>Systems</guimenu>
                            <guimenu>Virtual Systems</guimenu>
                        </menuchoice>. </para>
                </important>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>View inventoried ESXi host objects and resources by selecting <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>Systems</guimenu>
                        <guimenu>Virtual Systems</guimenu>
                    </menuchoice>.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <remark>Create a short section defining a virthostmgr-user then assign the correct
            role.</remark>
    </sect1>

</chapter>
