<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="bp.authentication.with.pam.and.ad">
    <title>Authentication Against &susemgr;</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>Authentication Via PAM</title>
        <para>As security measures become increasingly complex, SUSE Manager supports network-based
            authentication systems via Pluggable Authentication Modules (PAM). PAM is a suite of
            libraries that allows to integrate SUSE Manager with a centralized authentication
            mechanism, thus eliminating the need to remember multiple passwords. SUSE Manager
            supports LDAP, Kerberos, and other network-based authentication systems via PAM. To
            enable SUSE Manager to use PAM in your organization's authentication infrastructure,
            follow the steps below.</para>

        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>Set up a PAM service file (default location:
                        <filename>/etc/pam.d/susemanager</filename>) then enforce its use by adding
                    the following line to <filename>/etc/rhn/rhn.conf</filename>:</para>
                <screen>pam_auth_service = susemanager</screen>
                <note>
                    <para>This assumes the PAM service file is named susemanager.</para>
                </note>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>To enable a new or existing user to authenticate with PAM, proceed to the
                        <guimenu>Create User</guimenu> page and select the checkbox labeled
                    Pluggable Authentication Modules (PAM) positioned below the password and
                    password confirmation fields.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para> To authenticate a &slsa; system against Kerberos add the following lines to
                        <filename>/etc/pam.d/susemanager</filename>:</para>
                <screen> #%PAM-1.0
 auth     include        common-auth
 account  include        common-account
 password include        common-password
 session  include        common-session</screen>
                <note>
                    <para>To register a Red Hat Enterprise Linux System against Kerberos add the
                        following lines to <filename>/etc/pam.d/susemanager</filename></para>
                    <screen> #%PAM-1.0
 auth        required      pam_env.so
 auth        sufficient    pam_krb5.so no_user_check
 auth        required      pam_deny.so
 account     required      pam_krb5.so no_user_check</screen>
                </note>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>YaST can now be used to configure PAM, when packages such as yast2-ldap-client
                    and yast2-kerberos-client are installed; for detailed information on configuring
                    PAM, see the SUSE Linux Enterprise Server Security Guide <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_security/data/part_auth.html"
                    />. This example is not limited to Kerberos; it is generic and uses the current
                    server configuration. Note that only network based authentication services are
                    supported.</para>
                <important>
                    <title>Changing Passwords</title>
                    <para>Changing the password on the SUSE Manager Web interface changes only the
                        local password on the SUSE Manager server. But this password may not be used
                        at all if PAM is enabled for that user. In the above example, for instance,
                        the Kerberos password will not be changed.</para>
                </important>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Authentication Via eDirectory and PAM</title>
        <procedure>
            <step>
                <para>First check to ensure eDirectory authentication is working with your current
                    OS for example:</para>
                <screen>#getent passwd</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>If users are returned from eDirectory then create the following file:</para>
                <screen># cat /etc/pam.d/susemanager</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>And add the following content:</para>
                <screen> #%PAM-1.0
 auth     include        common-auth
 account  include        common-account
 password include        common-password
 session  include        common-session
 #</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Finally add the following lines to the &susemgr; conf file:</para>
                <screen> # grep -i pam /etc/rhn/rhn.conf
 pam_auth_service = susemanager</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>You may now create users with the same id that appears on eDirectory and mark
                    the Use PAM check-box from the SUSE Manager WebUI.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <para/>
    </sect1>
    <!-- ACTIVE DIRECTORY UPDATE LAST UPDATE FROM 2012 NEW IMAGES ETC. See Last link on : https://wiki.microfocus.com/index.php/SUSE_Manager/Authentication#AD_-_Active_Directory -->
</chapter>
