<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="bp.lifecycle">


    <title>Advanced Patch Lifecycle Management</title>

<sect1 xml:id="bp.chap.adv.life.mgr.covered">
    <title>Whats Covered Here?</title>
    
    <para>This chapter describes how to setup and configure a &susemgr; implementation to enable
        companies in the delivery of these often requested features: <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Automatic creation and archive of patch sets by quarter (or any other time
                    period)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Consistent method of patch promotion and delivery through numerous
                    landscapes and environments</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Exception process for handling patches that need to be excluded from a
                    patch cycle</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Environment creation with historical patch sets</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Minimal need for host channel subscription manipulation from
                    cradle-to-grave</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Support for service-pack migration using custom child channels</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Provides a foundation for using multiple organizations to maintain
                    systems.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="bp.chap.adv.patch.life.mgr.overview">
        <title>Patch Lifecycle Management Overview</title>
        <para>Keeping systems patched and secure remains one of the greatest ongoing challenges
            which you will face as an administrator. Both proprietary and open-source companies are
            constantly working to provide updates which fix flaws discovered within their software
            products.</para>

        <para>Adding to these pressures are requirements imposed by compliance initiatives such as: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>PCI-DSS (Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>SOX (Sarbanes-Oxley)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>HIPAA (Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>FIPS 140 (Federal Information Processing Standard)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>Included in most of these standards are rules which dictate frequency and
            time frames required for patching and often these schedules are modified due to the
            severity level of a specific patch.</para>

        <para>Businesses depend upon a changing landscape of applications covering a wide range of
            compute infrastructure. These may include physical and virtual hosts and have
            complicated application stacks. </para>
        <para>These applications may require the following: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A specific kernel version</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Strict uptime requirements</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specific run-time environments, (like Java)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specific Linux OS release</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specific configuration requirements</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Hardening and platform requirements</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Specific software versions</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>Additionally, many companies have created duplicate host environments such as: <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Production (PROD)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Development (DEV)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Quality Assurance (QA)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>User-acceptance/Testing (UAT)</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist> These landscapes mirror production environments and allow for testing or
            validation of applied changes to a system or set of systems. This means that you are
            required to manage, patch and report on at least one more complete set of hosts. </para>

        <sect2>
            <title>Important Terminology</title>
            <para>The following paragraphs provide an explanation of important terms used throughout
                this chapter.</para>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Landscape</title>
                <para>Describes one of several groups of Linux hosts. This is commonly used with
                    enterprise software deployments as a way to define the role/quality of a host.
                    Examples include, production (PROD), development (DEV), quality-assurance (QA),
                    user-acceptance/testing (UAT), etc.</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Environment</title>
                <para>Defined as a physical separation of Linux hosts, like Corporate (CORP), or
                    Store (STORE), or NPE (Non-production Environment).</para>
            </formalpara>
            <formalpara>
                <title>Organizations</title>
                <para>Defined as a separate management environment placed under the default
                    organization which is created during initial installation of a SUSE Manager
                    Server. Organizations in SUSE Manager will typically have separate credentials
                    required to administer them via the WebUI and any Linux hosts managed by SUSE
                    Manager will be registered to a single organization and only visible to this
                    organization.</para>
            </formalpara>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Example Scenario</title>
        <formalpara>
            <title>The Chameleon Corporation</title>
            <para>The world’s largest reptile and amphibian pet store whose headquarters are located
                in Yemen. This corporation has more than 1500 stores operating under the names
                    <emphasis>LizardsRUs</emphasis>, <emphasis>UnVeiledInc</emphasis> and
                    <emphasis>Chameleo-rama</emphasis> in five different countries. Due to
                compliance constraints, their patch lifecycle (both timing and delivery) is based on
                their corporate security policies, host environments, landscapes, and future
                management needs. The Chameleon Corporation must maintain the following requirements
                for managing patch and security updates to their Linux hosts:<itemizedlist>
                    <title>Requirement Summary</title>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The published Security Policy states: "All Linux systems need to be
                            up-to-date with the latest available updates, bug-fixes and enhancements
                            on a quarterly basis."</para>
                        <para>Quarters are defined as: <itemizedlist>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Q1: January 1st through March 31st</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Q2: April 1st through June 30th</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Q3: July 1st through September 30th</para>
                                </listitem>
                                <listitem>
                                    <para>Q4: October 1st through December 31st</para>
                                </listitem>
                            </itemizedlist></para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                        <para>The published Security Policy also states the need to patch all Linux
                            systems with “critical” security updates (CVSS score of 7 or greater)
                            within 1 month of release of the patch. This introduces a second
                            schedule that may overlap any existing patch roll-out.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>The company has 3 different host environments,
                                <emphasis>Corporate</emphasis>, <emphasis>Store</emphasis> and
                                <emphasis>NPE</emphasis>.These are partitioned using SUSE Manager
                            Organizations. Each SUSE Manager Organization has visibility into the
                            default SUSE Manager Organization’s software channels due to trusts, yet
                            the managed hosts are naturally grouped and managed by their
                            environment.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>There are at least 3 landscapes in each environment,
                                <emphasis>PROD</emphasis>,<emphasis>DEV</emphasis>, and
                                <emphasis>UAT</emphasis>.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>A “patch exceptions" process exists, as there is often a need to
                            account for the removal of patches (e.g. kernel updates) from a
                            roll-out. Some hosts may have hardware drivers or third party software
                            which depend upon specific kernel versions. This exception process would
                            be handled on a case-by-case basis.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </formalpara>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Requirements for Testing</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Implementation</title>
        <para/>

        <sect2>
            <title>Architecture</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Automation and Process Design</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Patch Promotion Cycle</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Exception and Escalation Channels</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Components</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Channels</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Activation Keys and Bootstrapping</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Scripts</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>
        <sect2>
            <title>Crontab Entries and Automation</title>
            <para/>
        </sect2>


    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Use Cases and Workflows</title>
        <para/>
    </sect1>



</chapter>
