<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="suma.choosing.dist.scheme">
    <title>Choosing a Distribution Scheme</title>

    <sect1>
        <title> SUSE Customer Center Connection (SCC) </title>
        <para>SUSE Customer Center (SCC) is the central place to manage your purchased SUSE
            subscriptions and entitlements, helping you access your update channels and get in
            contact with SUSE experts. The user-friendly interface gives you a centralized view of
            all your SUSE subscriptions, allowing you to easily find all subscription information
            you need. The improved registration provides faster access to your patches and updates.
            SUSE Customer Center is also designed to provide a common platform for your support
            requests and feedback. Discover a new way of managing your SUSE account and
            subscriptions via one interface—anytime, anywhere.</para>


    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sub.mgr.tool">
        <title>Subscription Management Tool for &sle; 12 SP1 </title>
        <para>Managing server subscriptions and support entitlements is easy with <link
                xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/login">SUSE Customer Center</link> (SCC) and the
            Subscription Management Tool (SMT).</para>
             <formalpara>
                 <title>Subscription Management Tool</title>
                 <para>SMT for &sle; helps customers manage their
            &sle; software updates while maintaining corporate firewall policy and regulatory
            compliance requirements. It establishes a proxy system for &scc; with repository and
            registration targets. This helps you centrally manage software updates within the
            firewall on a per-system basis while maintaining your corporate security policies
            and regulatory compliance. The downloadable Subscription Management Tool is
            integrated with SUSE Customer Center and provides a repository and synchronized
            registration target. This is very helpful in tracking entitlements in large
            deployments. The Subscription Management Tool also maintains all the capabilities of
            SUSE Customer Center while allowing a more secure centralized deployment. It is
            included with every SUSE Linux Enterprise subscription and, as a result, is fully
            supported. The Subscription Management Tool informs your SUSE Linux Enterprise
            devices of any available software updates. Each device then obtains the required
            software updates from the Subscription Management Tool. The introduction of the
            Subscription Management Tool improves the interaction among SUSE Linux Enterprise
            devices within the network and simplifies how they receive their system updates.
             </para></formalpara>
            
            <para>In a nutshell, the Subscription Management Tool for SUSE Linux Enterprise provides
                you with:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Assurance of firewall and regulatory compliance</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Reduced bandwidth use during software updates</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Full support under active subscription from SUSE></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Maintenance of existing customer interface with SUSE Customer
                        Center</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Accurate server entitlement tracking and effective measurement of
                        subscription usage</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Automated process to easily tally entitlement totals (no more
                        spreadsheets!)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Simple installation process that automatically synchronizes server
                        entitlement with SUSE Customer Center </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Disconnected Setup (DMZ)</title>
        <para/>

    </sect1>






</chapter>
