<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="bp.chapt.suma3.changes">
    <title>&susemgr; &productnumber3; and 2.1 Comparison</title>

    <sect1>
        <title>Overview of Changes</title>
        <para> You may already have experience managing your systems using SUSE Manager 2.1. The
            good news is all the features you are used to working with, (regarding the traditional
            spacewalk stack) have not changed. The only real exception is Monitoring which has been
            removed. (Further integration with Icinga will be added in the future). With SUSE
            Manager 3 you are now provided with two feature sets for management and therefore will
            need to make a decision on how the systems within your network will be managed. You may
            select a management method for each or your systems based on the traditional Spacewalk
            management stack or the new Salt management stack. </para>
        <important>
            <title>Selecting a Management Method</title>
            <para>You cannot and should not mix a single system with both methods although you can
                have Salt managed systems and traditionally managed systems within the same network.
                You may for example have a development department and assign all machines in this
                department as Salt minions likewise you could also have a production department and
                assign machines as traditional bootstrap clients. Just remember a single machine is
                either Spacewalk or Salt never both.</para>
        </important>

        <para/>
    </sect1>






</chapter>
