<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="suma.choosing.dist.scheme">
 <title>Managing Your Subscriptions</title>
 <para>
  There are two methods for managing your subscriptions. Both methods
  access &scc; and provide specialized benefits.
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Directly connecting to &scc; is the recommended default way of managing
    your &susemgr; Server.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If you have special network security requirements which do not allow access
    from your internal network to the internet then you may use a &sle; 12
    Server running the Subscription Management Tool (SMT).
    This tool will contact &scc; from a system connected to the
    external network and obtain updates for your clients which you may then
    mount on your internal &susemgr; Server. This is the preferred method for
    managing client systems within a highly secure network infrastructure.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <sect1>
  <title>SUSE Customer Center (SCC)</title>

  <para>
   SUSE Customer Center (SCC) is the central place to manage your purchased
   SUSE subscriptions, helping you access your update channels
   and get in contact with SUSE experts. The user-friendly interface gives you
   a centralized view of all your SUSE subscriptions, allowing you to easily
   find all subscription information you need. The improved registration
   provides faster access to your patches and updates. SUSE Customer Center is
   also designed to provide a common platform for your support requests and
   feedback. Discover a new way of managing your SUSE account and subscriptions
   via one interface—anytime, anywhere. For more information on using &scc;
   see: <link xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/docs/userguide"/>
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="sub.mgr.tool">
  <title>Subscription Management Tool (SMT) and Disconnected Setup (DMZ)</title>

  <para>
   If it is not possible to connect SUSE Manager directly or via a proxy to the
   Internet, a disconnected setup in combination with Subscription Management
   Tool (SMT) is the recommended solution. In this scenario, SMT stays in an
   “external” network with a connection to &scc; and synchronizes the
   software channels and repositories on a removable storage medium. Then you
   separate the storage medium from SMT, and mount it locally on your SUSE
   Manager server to read the updated data.
  </para>

  <para>
   The following procedure will guide you through using SMT.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>SMT: Fetching Repository Data from &scc;</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Configure SMT in the external network with SUSE Customer Center (SCC). For
     details about configuring SMT with &sle; 12, see:
     <link
                        xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/book_smt/data/book_smt.html"
                    />
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Using SMT, mirror all required repositories.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Create a "database replacement file" (for example,
     <filename>/tmp/dbrepl.xml</filename>.
    </para>
<screen>smt-sync --createdbreplacementfile /tmp/dbrepl.xml</screen>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="pro.mgr.tool.mount.storage">
    <para>
     Mount a removable storage medium such as an external hard disk or USB
     flash drive.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Export the data to the mounted medium:
    </para>
<screen>smt-sync --todir /media/disk/
smt-mirror --dbreplfile /tmp/dbrepl.xml --directory /media/disk \
           --fromlocalsmt -L /var/log/smt/smt-mirror-export.log</screen>
    <important>
     <title>Write Permissions for SMT User</title>
     <para>
      The directory being written too must be writeable for the same user as
      the smt daemon (user=smt). The smt user setting is defined in
      <filename>/etc/smt.conf</filename>. You can check if the correct user is
      specified via the following command:
     </para>
<screen># egrep '^smtUser' /etc/smt.conf</screen>
    </important>
    <note>
     <title>Keeping A Disconnected Server Up-to-date</title>
     <para>
      <command>smt-sync</command> also exports your subscription
      data. To keep SUSE Manager up-to-date with your subscriptions,
      you must frequently import and export this data.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Unmount the storage medium and carry it securely to your &susemgr;
     &productnumber; Server.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   The next procedure will show you how to update your server from the SMT
   media.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Updating Your &susemgr; Server from the Storage Medium</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Mount the storage medium on your &susemgr; server (for example, at
     <filename>/media/disk</filename>).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Specify the local path on the &susemgr; server in
     <literal>/etc/rhn/rhn.conf</literal>:
    </para>
<screen>server.susemanager.fromdir = /media/disk</screen>
    <para>
     This setting is mandatory for &scc; and <command>mgr-sync</command>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Restart Tomcat:
    </para>
<!-- bsc#977196 -->
<!-- <screen>rctomcat6 restart</screen> -->
<screen>systemctl restart tomcat</screen>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="pro.mgr.tool.sync">
    <para>
     Before performing another operation on the server execute a full sync:
    </para>
<screen>mgr-sync refresh   # SCC (fromdir in rhn.conf required!)</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     <command>mgr-sync</command> can now be executed normally:
    </para>
<screen>mgr-sync list channels
mgr-sync add channel channel-label</screen>
    <warning>
     <title>Data Corruption</title>
     <para>
      The disk must always be available at the same mount point. To avoid data
      corruption, do not trigger a sync, if the storage medium is not mounted.
      If you have already added a channel from a local repository path, you
      will not be able to change its URL to point to a different path
      afterwards.
     </para>
    </warning>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Up-to-date data is now available on your &susemgr; server and is ready for
   updating client systems. According to your maintenance windows or update
   schedule refresh the data on the storage medium with SMT.
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Refreshing Data on the Storage Medium from SMT</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     On your &susemgr; server, unmount the storage medium and carry it to your
     SMT.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     On your SMT system, continue with <xref linkend="pro.mgr.tool.sync"/>.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Data Corruption</title>
     <para>
      The storage medium must always be available at the same mount point. To
      avoid data corruption, do not trigger a sync if the storage medium is not
      mounted.
     </para>
    </warning>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   This concludes using SMT with &susemgr; &productnumber;.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
