<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="suma.choosing.dist.scheme">
    <title>Managing Entitlement Methods</title>
    <para>There are two methods for managing your subscriptions and entitlements. Both management
        methods access &scc; and provide specialized benefits. Directly connecting to &scc; is the
        recommended default way of managing your &susemgr; Server. If you have special network
        security requirements which do not allow access from your internal network the internet then
        you may use a &sle; 12 SP1 Server running the Subscription Management Tool (SMT) for
        maintaining your entitlements. This tool will contact &scc; and obtain updates for your
        clients which you may then mount on your &susemgr; Server  for providing updates. This is
        the preferred method for managing client systems within a highly secure network
        infrastructure.</para>
    <sect1>
        <title> Overview SUSE Customer Center (SCC) </title>
        <para>SUSE Customer Center (SCC) is the central place to manage your purchased SUSE
            subscriptions and entitlements, helping you access your update channels and get in
            contact with SUSE experts. The user-friendly interface gives you a centralized view of
            all your SUSE subscriptions, allowing you to easily find all subscription information
            you need. The improved registration provides faster access to your patches and updates.
            SUSE Customer Center is also designed to provide a common platform for your support
            requests and feedback. Discover a new way of managing your SUSE account and
            subscriptions via one interface—anytime, anywhere. </para>
        
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>For more information on using &scc; see: <link
                xlink:href="https://scc.suse.com/docs/userguide">&scc; User Guide</link></para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="sub.mgr.tool">
        <title>Subscription Management Tool (SMT) and Disconnected Setup (DMZ)</title>
        <para></para>
       
    </sect1>








</chapter>
