<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="bp.chap.salt.minion.scaleability">
 <title>Salt Minion Scalability</title>

 <sect1>
  <title>Salt Minion Onboarding Rate</title>
  <para>The rate at which SUSE Manager can on-board minions (accept Salt keys) is limited and
   depends on hardware resources. On-boarding minions at a faster rate than SUSE Manager is
   configured for will build up a backlog of unprocessed keys slowing the process and potentially
   exhausting resources. It is recommended to limit the acceptance key rate pro-grammatically. A
   safe starting point would be to on-board a minion every 15 seconds, which can be implemented via
   the following command:</para>
  <screen>for k in $(salt-key -l un|grep -v Unaccepted); do salt-key -y -a $k; sleep 15; done </screen>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="bp.chap.salt.minion.scaleability.unaccepted">
  <title>Minions Running with Unaccepted Salt Keys</title>
  <para> Minions which have not been on-boarded, (minions running with unaccepted Salt keys) consume
   resources, in particular inbound network bandwidth for ~2.5 Kb/s per minion. 1000 idle minions
   will consume around ~2.5 Mb/s, and this number will drop to almost 0 once on-boarding has been
   completed. Limit non-onboarded systems for optimal performance. </para>

  <para> Salt's official documentation suggests the maximum number of opened files should be set to
   at least 2 × the minion count. Current default is 16384, which is sufficient for ~8000 minions.
   For larger installations, this number may be increased by editing the following line in
    <filename>/usr/lib/systemd/system/salt-master.service</filename>: </para>
  <screen>LimitNOFILE=16384</screen>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 xml:id="bp.chap.salt.minion.scaleability.timeouts">
  <!--
      https://wiki.microfocus.com/index.php?title=SUSE_Manager/SaltTimeoutsForMinions&action=edit
  -->
  <title>Salt Timeouts</title>
  <sect2>
   <title>Background Information</title>
   <para> Salt features two timeout parameters called <literal>timeout</literal> and
     <literal>gather_job_timeout</literal> that are relevant during the execution of Salt commands
    and jobs—it does not matter whether they are triggered using the command line interface or API.
    These two parameters are explained in the following article. </para>

   <para> This is a normal workflow when all minions are well reachable: </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para> A salt command or job is executed: </para>
     <screen>salt '*' test.ping</screen>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Salt master publishes the job with the targeted minions into the Salt PUB channel.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Minions take that job and start working on it. </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> Salt master is looking at the Salt RET channel to gather responses from the minions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para> If Salt master gets all responses from targeted minions, then everything is completed
      and Salt master will return a response containing all the minion responses. </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para> If some of the minions are down during this process, the workflow continues as follows: </para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para> If <literal>timeout</literal> is reached before getting all expected responses from the
      minions, then Salt master would trigger an aditional job (a Salt <command>find_job</command>
      job) targeting only pending minions to check whether the job is already running on the minion.
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> Now <literal>gather_job_timeout</literal> is evaluated. A new counter is now triggered.
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> If this new <command>find_job</command> job responses that the original job is actually
      running on the minion, then Salt master will wait for that minion's response. </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para> In case of reaching <literal>gather_job_timeout</literal> without having any response
      from the minion (neither for the initial <command>test.ping</command> nor for the
       <command>find_job</command> job), Salt master will return with only the gathered responses
      from the responding minions. </para>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>

   <para> By default, &susemgr; globally sets <literal>timeout</literal> and
     <literal>gather_job_timeout</literal> to 120 seconds. So, in the worst case, a Salt call
    targeting unreachable minions will end up <emphasis>with 240 seconds of waiting</emphasis> until
    getting a response. </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="bp.chap.salt.minion.scaleability.timeouts.presence">
   <title>A Presence Ping Mechanism for Unreachable Salt Minions</title>
   <para> In order to prevent waiting until timeouts are reached when some minions are down, &suse;
    introduced a so-called "presence mechanism" for Salt minions. </para>

   <para> On &susemgr; 3.0.5 and later, this presence mechanism checks for unreachable Salt minions
    when &susemgr; is performing synchronous calls to these minions, and it excludes unreachable
    minions from that call. Synchronous calls are going to be displaced in favor of asynchronous
    calls but currently still being used during some workflows. </para>
   <para> The presence mechanism triggers a Salt <command>test.ping</command> with a custom and
    fixed short Salt timeout values. Default Salt values for the presence ping are: <literal>timeout
     = 4</literal> and <literal>gather_job_timeout = 1</literal>. This way, we can quickly detect
    which targeted minions are unreachable, and then exclude them from the synchronous call. </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Overriding Salt Presence Timeout Values</title>
   <para> &susemgr; administrators can increase or decrease default presence ping timeout values by
    removing the comment markers (<literal>#</literal>) and setting the desired values for
     <literal>salt_presence_ping_timeout</literal> and
     <literal>salt_presence_ping_gather_job_timeout</literal> options in
     <filename>/etc/rhn/rhn.conf</filename>: </para>
   <screen># SUSE Manager presence timeouts for Salt minions
# salt_presence_ping_timeout = 4
# salt_presence_ping_gather_job_timeout = 1</screen>
  </sect2>
  <sect2>
   <title>Salt SSH Minions (SSH Push)</title>
   <para> Salt SSH minions are slightly different that regular minions (zeromq). Salt SSH minions do
    not use Salt PUB/RET channels but a wrapper Salt command inside of an SSH call. Salt
     <literal>timeout</literal> and <literal>gather_job_timeout</literal> are not playing a role
    here. </para>
   <para> &susemgr; defines a timeout for SSH connections in <filename>/etc/rhn/rhn.conf</filename>: </para>
   <screen># salt_ssh_connect_timeout = 180</screen>
   <para> The presence ping mechanism is also working with SSH minions. In this case, &susemgr; will
    use <literal>salt_presence_ping_timeout</literal> to override the default timeout value for SSH
    connections. </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
