<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="chapt.bp.channel.management">

  <!-- ################################################################################# -->
  <!-- Draft 1 Channel Management-->
  <!-- ################################################################################# -->


  <title>Channel and Repository Management</title>

  <sect1 xml:id="chapt.bp.channel.management.intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This chapter discusses the crucial topic of channel design within the &susemgr;
      environment and provides an introduction to channel and repository management concepts. This
      chapter will go over base and child channel relationships, deployment and maintenance of
      vendor and custom channels, creating repositories, working with GPG keys and content staging.
      To following along with this chapter it is assumed that &susemgr; is connected to &scc;.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 xml:id="chapt.bp.channel.management.channel.design.concepts">
    <title>The Importance of Channel Design</title>
    <para>The design of your channels influences all other component interaction within &susemgr;
      and as such, channel design requires careful planning and a concrete understanding of channel
      terminology. While re-working channels after initial setup is certainly possible, in large
      environments this will become an increasingly difficult task. Therefore it is important to
      plan your channel implementation with this consideration in mind, specifically when regarding
      large production environments. </para>

    <para>Channels in &susemgr; are collections of software packages. Like other media types
      channels contain software packages, patches and updates for client systems. Channels also
      provide an administrator with strict controls as to which packages may be installed on client
      systems and make an organizations application life cycle easier to manage.</para>


    <sect2>
      <title>Channel Terminology</title>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Channels and Repositories</title>
        <para>A channel could also be called a package or repository manager. A channel is a
          collection of RPMs and patch data. Every base channel contains metadata about its packages
          specific to a product release and architecture. A term that is often confused with
          channels, is <systemitem>repository</systemitem>. A repository is a storage location from
          which software packages may be retrieved and installed. A repository can be either local
          or external. A repository contains a set of packages similar to a channel however a single
          &susemgr; channel can contain many repositories. A single repository contains package
          sets. Multiple repositories can be assigned as child channels to a single base channel.
        </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Base Channels</title>
        <para>Base channels are built on a specific architecture and product, for example a &sle; or
          RHEL release. A base channel may contain one or more child channels. A traditional client
          or Salt minion may only be assigned one base channel. If the base channel is a clone
          (copy) of a SUSE channel it also contains the meta information required to perform a SUSE
          Manager support pack migration.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Child channels</title>
        <para>These channels belong to a single base channel and are from the same architecture as
          the base SLES or RHEL release channel. A registered system may have one or more child
          channels, but all children must belong to the same base channel.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Patches</title>
        <para>Patches are a collection of packages which belong together and aid in solving security
          issues, contain bug fixes or to simply provide an update. The data within a patch is
          gathered together and termed patches. Regarding SUSE Manager, most actions performed
          within software channels are executed using these patches. </para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Packages</title>
        <para>Packages are RPMs that contain necessary files: configuration, binaries, scripts, as
          well as pre and post installation scripts.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Clones</title>
        <para>A clone is a copy of a channel and will include exactly the same information as the
          original channel. If the original channel receives updates after the clone has been
          created, these changes need to be updated (or cloned) to the cloned channel. This is a
          manual process which can be automated with the standard SLES tools. Cloning is especially
          useful in life-cycle management. For more information on working with cloned channels and
          life-cycle design see: <remark>add link to Jeff's guide</remark>
        </para>
      </formalpara>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction to SUSE Customer Center Channels</title>
    <para/>

    <sect2>
      <title>Base and Child Channels</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Subscribing to Channels</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Channel Availability</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Tools and Repositories</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Building Custom Packages</title>
    <para/>

    <sect2>
      <title>Building Packages for Custom Channels</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>RPM Benefits</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>RPM Guidelines</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Digital Signatures for SUSE Packages</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Generating GNuPG Keys</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Signing Packages</title>
      <para/>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Custom Channel and Package Management</title>
    <para/>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Channel Management Privileges</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Manage Software Channels</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Managed Software Channel Details</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Manage Software Packages</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Creating a Software Channel</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Assigning Packages to Software Channels</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Cloning Software Channels</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Deleting Software Channels</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
<!--
  <sect1>
    <title>Custom Errata Management</title>
    <para/>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Manage Errata</title>
    <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Manage Errata Details</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Creating and Editing Errata</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Assigning Packages to Errata</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Cloning Errata</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
-->
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Uploading and Maintaining Custom Packages</title>
    <para/>
    <sect2>
      <title>Uploading Packages to SUSE Manager Proxy</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Uploading Packages to SUSE Manager Server </title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Configuring RHN Push</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Using RHN Push</title>
      <para></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


</chapter>
