<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml" 
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
"-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<!-- ################################################################################# -->
<!-- This chapter under construction incomplete data and placeholder text blocks. -->
<!-- ################################################################################# -->

<chapter id="chapt.bp.channel.management">
  <title>Channel Management</title>

  <sect1 id="chapt.bp.channel.management.intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>This chapter discusses the critical topic of channel design within &susemgr; and provides
      a foundational overview of channel management concepts within a &susemgr; network. This
      includes naming, base and child channel relationships, deployment and maintenance of vendor
      and custom channels for &susemgr; Server and &susemgrproxy; as well as the &susemgr; channel
      life cycle and staging. This chapter also provides information about repositories, cloning,
      and security options within &susemgr;. </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="chapt.bp.channel.management.channel.design.concepts">
    <title>Channel Design Concepts</title>

    <para>The design of channels influence all other components within &susemgr; and as such,
      channel design requires careful consideration and a concrete understanding of channel
      terminology. While re-working channels after initial setup is possible, in large environments
      this will become increasingly difficult. Therefore it is important to plan your channel life
      cycle implementation with this consideration in mind, specifically regarding large system
      environments. </para>
    <para>Channels in &susemgr; represent the installation media for your clients. Like other media
      types channels contain software packages, patches and updates for client systems. Channels
      also provide an administrator with strict controls as to which packages may be installed on
      client systems and make an organizations application life cycle easier to manage.</para>
      <!-- need to add links here going to the API and CLI
        documentation! -->
      
      <para> There are
      three kinds of channels used within &susemgr;.</para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>SUSE Vendor Channels</title>
      <para>SUSE Vendor Channels are maintained by SUSE Linux and cannot be changed or
        modified.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Custom Channels</title>
      <para>Custom Channels are created according to your infrastructure requirements and include
        specific packages relevant to your system needs. These may be changed and modified.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Repositories</title>
      <para>Repositories are used to import packages from existing repositories into a software
        channel or channels.</para>
    </formalpara>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="chapt.bp.channel.management.base.child.relationships">
    <title> Base Channels vs. Child Channels</title>
    <para>It is important to understand channel hierarchy within &susemgr;. There are
        <systemitem>base</systemitem> channels and <systemitem>child</systemitem> channels. Channels
      are organized into a tree like system. A client system needs to be assigned a base channel as
      this provides it's main media sources. A client may only have one base channel assigned to it,
      but a base channel may be assigned multiple child channels. A base channel could also be
      referred to as a parent channel to which all child channels belong.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Base(Parent) Channels and Child Channels.</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="base-child-channels.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Relationship Between Products and Channels</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Organization Credentials</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Adding Products</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Channel Cloning</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title> Cloning Channels by Date</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Channel Lifecycle Management</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Channel Security</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Signed Third party packages</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Signed Internal Packages</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>GPG key usage</title>
    <para/>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
