<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="bp.live.patching">
 <title>Live Patching with SUSE Manager</title>
 <sect1>
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para> Under normal circumstances a system needs to be rebooted after a kernel update. SLE Live
   Patching allows you skipping the reboot by applying a subset of Linux kernel releases injected
   via kGraft live patching technology. </para>

  <para> In the following sections you will learn how to use SLE Live Patching to avoid the typical
   reboot requirement after updating a system kernel. </para>

  <para> For in depth information covering kGraft use, see <link
    xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/sles-12/singlehtml/book_sle_admin/book_sle_admin.html#cha.kgraft"
   />. </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Initial Setup Requirements</title>

  <para> To work with SLE Live Patching the following expectations are assumed: </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para> &susemgr; 3.0 or later fully updated. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> At least 1 Salt Minion running SLES 12 SP1 or later and registered with &susemgr;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> The matching SLES 12 SPx channels including the SLE Live Patching child channel fully
     synced. </para>
   </listitem>
   <!--  <listitem>
    <para> spacewalk-utils package installed on the &susemgr; server: </para>
    <screen>&prompt.root;zypper in spacewalk-utils</screen>
   </listitem> -->
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Live Patching Setup</title>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Subscribe all systems to be managed via live patching to your fully synced live patching
     child channels within your systems base channel by browsing to <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Software Channels</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. Select both live patching channels and change subscription. </para>
    <note>
     <para> When subscribing to a channel that contains a product, the product package will
      automatically be installed on traditionaly registered systems and added to the package state
      on Salt managed systems. For Salt managed systems please apply the highstate to push these
      changes to your systems. </para>
    </note>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_channels.png" width="400"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_channels.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Use the search field listed under <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Packages</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Install</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> to install the latest <filename>kgraft</filename> package to all systems to be
     managed via live patching. </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_kgraft_install.png" width="400"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_kgraft_install.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Apply the highstate to enable live patching: </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_apply_highstate.png" width="400"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_apply_highstate.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Once the highstate has been applied on Salt systems or the package has been installed on
     traditional systems browse to the systems details page for confirmation that live patching has
     been enabled. You can check the live patching state listed under the <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>System Info</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Kernel</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> table field: </para>
    <informalfigure>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_successful.png" width="400"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="enable_live_patching_successful.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1>
  <title>Cloning Channels</title>

  <para> It is considered best practice to clone a vendor channel that will be modified into a new
   channel with one of the following prefix names: (dev, testing, and prod). In the following
   procedure you will clone the default vendor channel into a new channel named
    <filename>dev-sles12-sp3-pool-x86_64</filename> using the command line. </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Open a terminal and as root enter: </para>
    <screen># spacewalk-manage-channel-lifecycle -list-channels
Spacewalk Username: admin
Spacewalk Password: 
Channel tree:

 1. sles12-sp3-pool-x86_64
      \__ sle-live-patching12-pool-x86_64-sp3
      \__ sle-live-patching12-updates-x86_64-sp3
      \__ sle-manager-tools12-pool-x86_64-sp3
      \__ sle-manager-tools12-updates-x86_64-sp3
      \__ sles12-sp3-updates-x86_64  </screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Now use the <emphasis>-init</emphasis> argument to automatically create a new development
     clone of the original vendor channel: </para>
    <screen>spacewalk-manage-channel-lifecycle -init -c sles12-sp3-pool-x86_64</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1>
  <title>Removing Non-live Kernel Patches from the Cloned Channels</title>

  <para> In the following procedure you will remove all kernel patch updates located in the
   dev-sles12-sp3-updates-x86_64 channel that require a reboot. </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Check the current kernel version in use on your client: </para>
    <screen># uname -r
3.12.62-60.64.8-default</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> From the SUSE Manager WebUI select<menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Manage Software Channels</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>
      <guimenu>dev-sles12-sp3-updates-x86_64</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Patches</guimenu>
      <guimenu>List/Remove</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. Type <literal>kernel</literal> in the search field. Find the kernel version that
     matches the kernel in use on your minion. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Remove all kernel update versions that are later than the current kernel. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Your channel is now ready to promote for testing SLE Live Patching. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1>
  <title>Promoting Channels</title>

  <para> The following procedure will guide you through promoting and cloning a development channel
   to a testing channel. You will change the subscription from the dev repositories on your client
   to the new testing channel repositories. You will also add the SLE Live Patching child channels
   to your client. </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Promote and clone the <literal>dev-sles12-sp3-pool-x86_64</literal> to a new testing
     channel: </para>
    <screen>&prompt.root;spacewalk-manage-channel-lifecycle -promote -c dev-sles12-sp3-pool-x86_64</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> From the &susemgr; &webui; under the <guimenu>Systems</guimenu> tab select your client
     system to view the <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page. Select <menuchoice>
      <guimenu>Software</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Software Channels</guimenu>
     </menuchoice>. From the Software Channels page you can edit which channels a system is
     subscribed to. Select the new base software channel, in this case it should be
      <literal>test-sles12-sp3-pool-x86_64</literal>. Click the <guimenu>Confirm</guimenu> button to
     switch the Base Software Channel and finalize it by clicking the <guimenu>Modify Base Software
      Channel</guimenu> button. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> From the <guimenu>Software Channels</guimenu> page select and add both SLE Live Patching
     child channels by clicking the <guimenu>Change Subscriptions</guimenu> button. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </sect1>

 <sect1>
  <title>Applying Live Patches to a Kernel</title>

  <para> The following procedure will guide you through selecting and viewing available CVE Patches
   (Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures) then applying these kernel updates using the new SLE Live
   Patching feature. </para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Select your SLES 12 SP3 minion from the <guimenu>Systems</guimenu> page to view its
      <guimenu>System Details</guimenu>. Once you have added the SLES 12 SP3 Updates child channel
     to your client, you should see several <literal>Critical</literal> software updates available.
     Click on <literal>Critical</literal> to see a list of available patches. Select any of these
     patches listed with the following synopsis: <emphasis>Important: Security update for the Linux
      kernel</emphasis>. All fixed security bugs will be listed along with their number. For
     example:(CVE-2016-8666) </para>
    <important>
     <title>Reboot Icon</title>
     <para> Normal or non-live kernel patches always require a reboot. In SUSE Manager these are
      represented by a <literal>Reboot Required</literal> icon located next to the
       <literal>Security</literal> shield icon. </para>
    </important>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> You can search for individual CVE's by selecting the <guimenu>Audit</guimenu> tab from
     the navigation menu. Try searching for <literal>CVE-2016-8666</literal>. You will see that the
     patch is available in the vendor update channel and the systems it applies to will be listed.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>



  <important>
   <title>CVE Availability</title>
   <para> Not all security issues can be fixed by applying a live patch. Some security issues can
    only be fixed by applying a full kernel update and will required a reboot. The assigned CVE
    numbers for these issues are not included in live patches. A CVE audit will display this
    requirement. </para>
  </important>

 </sect1>
</chapter>
