<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC
  "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<sect1>
 <title>Legal Notice</title>

 <para os="sled;sles">
  All content is copyright &copy; 2006&ndash;
<?dbtimestamp format="Y"?>
  SUSE LLC. All rights reserved.
 </para>

 <para os="sled;sles">
  This manual is protected under SUSE intellectual property rights. By
  reproducing, duplicating or distributing this manual you explicitly agree
  to conform to the terms and conditions of this license agreement.
 </para>

 <para os="sled;sles">
  This manual may be freely reproduced, duplicated and distributed either as
  such or as part of a bundled package in electronic and/or printed format,
  provided however that the following conditions are fulfilled:
 </para>

 <simplelist os="sled;sles">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    That this copyright notice and the names of authors and contributors
    appear clearly and distinctively on all reproduced, duplicated and
    distributed copies. That this manual, specifically for the printed
    format, is reproduced and/or distributed for noncommercial use only. The
    express authorization of Novell, Inc must be obtained prior to any other
    use of any manual or part thereof.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </simplelist>

 <para os="sled;sles">
  For SUSE or Novell trademarks, see the Novell Trademark and Service Mark list
  <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/company/legal/trademarks/tmlist.html"/>.
  All other third party
  trademarks are the property of their respective owners. A trademark symbol
  (&reg;, &trade; etc.) denotes a SUSE or Novell trademark; an asterisk (*)
  denotes a third party trademark.
 </para>

 <para os="sled;sles">
  All information found in this book has been compiled with utmost attention
  to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. Neither
  SUSE LLC, SUSE LINUX Products GmbH, the authors, nor the translators
  shall be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof.
 </para>

 <para os="osuse">
  Copyright&copy; 2006&ndash;<?dbtimestamp format="Y"?>
  SUSE LLC and contributors. All rights reserved.
 </para>

 <para os="osuse">
  Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
  under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or (at
  your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant Section being this copyright
  notice and license. A copy of the license version 1.2 is included in the
  section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation License</quote>.
 </para>

 <para os="osuse">
  For SUSE or Novell trademarks, see the Novell Trademark and Service Mark list
  <ulink url="http://www.novell.com/company/legal/trademarks/tmlist.html"/>.
  All other third party
  trademarks are the property of their respective owners. A trademark symbol
  (&reg;, &trade; etc.) denotes a SUSE or Novell trademark; an asterisk (*) denotes
  a third party trademark.
 </para>

 <para os="osuse">
  All information found in this book has been compiled with utmost attention
  to detail. However, this does not guarantee complete accuracy. Neither
  SUSE LLC, SUSE LINUX Products GmbH, the authors, nor the translators
  shall be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof.
 </para>
</sect1>
