<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC
  "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="ch-intro-reference" >
<!--status="rfc"-->
 <title>&susemgr; Overview</title><indexterm>
 <primary>&susemgr;</primary>
 <secondary>Overview</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>Overview</primary></indexterm>
<!--
 <para>
  Have you ever read about a new version of a software package and wanted to
  install it but could not find it?
 </para>
 <para>
  Have you ever tried to find an RPM through an Internet search engine or an
  RPM repository and been linked to an unknown site?
 </para>
 <para>
  Have you ever searched for an RPM but instead found only source files that
  you had to compile yourself?
 </para>
 <para>
  Have you ever spent hours or even days visiting different websites to see
  if you have the latest packages installed on your system, only to have to
  do it again in a few months?
 </para>
 <para>
  Those days are over with &susemgr; and the &ncc; (NCC). &susemgr; provides
  the solution to all your system software management needs.
 </para>
-->
 <para><remark>emap: check if up-2-date</remark>
  &susemgr; is a server solution for managing
<!-- a single &suselinux;
  system or -->
  a network of &sle; or &rhel; systems.
  All security alerts, bug fix alerts, and enhancement alerts (collectively
  known as patch alerts) can be downloaded directly from &suse;, or Novell,
  or your own custom collection. You can even schedule updates for delivery
  to your system immediately after release.
 </para>
 <para>
  The main components of &susemgr; are:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    the update agent (<command>rhn_check</command>),
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    the &susemgr; Web interface, whether this is hosted by a &susemgr; or fed
    through a proxy server,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    &susemgr; daemon.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  &susemgr; daemon enables channel subscription, package installs, and
  management of system profiles. <phrase os="hidden">See <xref linkend="ch-up2date"/> for
	  further information.</phrase>
 </para>
 <para>
  The &susemgr; daemon (<command>rhnsd</command>) runs in the background as
  a service and probes &susemgr; for notifications and updates at set time
  intervals (see <xref linkend="ch-rhnsd"/> for further information). This
  daemon is necessary in order to schedule updates or other actions through
  the Web interface.
 </para>
 <remark role="generic">
  2011-01-27 - ke: mentioning low level reg tool?
 </remark>
 <remark>toms 2011-01-24: @MGR: According to bnc#666953, this section
  is not needed</remark>
 <para>
  Find out more about &susemgr; at
  <ulink url="http://www.suse.com/products/suse-manager/technical-information/"/>.
 </para>
 <sect1 id="s1-intro-rhn-workgroup">
  <title>Management</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr;  Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Management</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   In addition to the features offered in the &susemgr; update subscription
   level, the &susemgr; management subscription service allows you to manage
   your network of &sle; systems, users, and system groups through its
   <guimenu>System Set Manager</guimenu> interface.
  </para>

  <para>
   &susemgr; management is based on the concept of organizations. Each
   management-level &suse; customer has the ability to establish users who
   have administration privileges to system groups. An organization
   administrator has overall control over each &susemgr; organization with
   the ability to add and remove systems and users. When users other than
   the &susemgr; administrator log into the &susemgr; Web interface, they see only
   the systems they have permission to administer.
  </para>

  <para>
   The &susemgr; features available to you depend on the subscription level
   for each &sle; system. With each management subscription, you receive the
   functionality to update users, plus:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Package Profile Comparison — Compare the package set on one system
     with the package sets of similar systems with one click.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Search Systems — Search through systems based on a number of
     criteria: packages, networking information, even hardware asset tags.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System Grouping — Web servers, database servers, workstations and
     other workload-focused systems may be grouped so that each set can be
     administered in common ways.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Multiple Administrators — Administrators may be given rights to
     particular system groups, easing the burden of system management over
     very large organizations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     System Set Manager — You can apply actions to sets of systems
     instead of applying them to each system individually, work with
     members of a predefined system group, or work with an ad-hoc
     collection of systems. With a single action, install software
     packages on each system in the set, subscribe the systems to a
     new channel, or apply all patches to them.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Batch Processing — Compiling a list of outdated packages for a
     thousand systems would take days even for an experienced sysadmin.
     &susemgr; can do it for you in seconds.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="s1-intro-rhn-provisioning">
  <title>Provisioning</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Provisioning</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Provisioning service level is optional and encompasses all of the
   features offered in the update and management subscription levels. It is
   designed to allow you to deploy and manage your network of &sle; systems,
   users, and system groups.
  </para>

  <para>
   Like management, provisioning is based on an organization. It takes
   this concept a step further by enabling customers with provisioning
   entitlements to autoinstall&mdash;using &ay; or Kickstart&mdash;
   to reconfigure, track, and revert systems on the fly.
  </para>
  <para>
   In addition to all of the features mentioned in lower service levels,
   Provisioning provides:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Autoinstalling — Systems with provisioning entitlements may be
     automatically installed via &ay; or Kickstart. This process can be
     adjusted to your needs with various options, including the type of
     bootloader, time zone, packages included/excluded, and IP address
     ranges allowed. Even GPG and SSL keys can be pre-configured.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Client Configuration — &susemgr; customers may use &susemgr; to
     manage the configuration files on provisioning-entitled systems. Users
     can upload files to custom configuration channels on the Satellite,
     verify local configuration files against those stored on the Satellite,
     and deploy files from the Satellite.
    </para>
   </listitem>
<!-- FIXME: checkit
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Snapshot Rollbacks — Provisioning-level users have the ability to
     revert the package profile and RHN settings of systems. &susemgr;
     customers can also roll back local configurations files. This is
     possible because snapshots are captured whenever an action takes place
     on a system. These snapshots identify groups, channels, packages, and
     configuration files.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      With snapshot roll backs you can revert <emphasis>certain</emphasis>
      changes to a system, but not in every scenario. For example, you can
      roll back a set of RPM packages, but rolling back across multiple
      update levels is not supported.
     </para>
    </note>
   </listitem>
   -->
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Custom System Information — Provisioning customers can add any type
     of information about their registered systems via custom keys and
     values. This differs from system profile information, which is
     generated automatically, and also from the Notes, which are completely
     unrestricted. Custom system information allows you to create keys of
     your choice and assign searchable values for these key to each
     provisioning-entitled system. For instance, this feature allows you to
     specify the cubicle in which each system is located and search through
     all registered systems according to their cubicle.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="s1-intro-rhn-monitoring">
  <title>Monitoring</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Monitoring</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Monitoring entitlements are available to &susemgr; customers with &sle;
   systems.
  </para>

  <para>
   Monitoring allows an organization to install probes that can immediately
   detect failures and identify performance degradation before it becomes
   critical. Used properly, the monitoring entitlement can provide insight
   into the applications, services, and devices on each system.
  </para>

  <para>
   Specifically, monitoring provides:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Probes — Dozens of probes can be run against each system. These range
     from simple <command>ping</command> checks to custom remote programs
     designed to return valuable data.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Notification — Alerts can be sent to email addresses with
     contact methods identified by you when a probe changes state. Each
     probe notification can be sent to a different method or address.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Central Status — The results of all probes are summarized on a single
     <guimenu>Probe Status</guimenu> page, with the systems affected broken
     down by state.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Reporting — By selecting a probe and identifying the particular
     metric and a range of time, you can generate graphs and event logs
     depicting precisely how the probe has performed. This can be
     instrumental in predicting and preventing costly system failures.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Probe Suites — Groups of probes may be assigned to a system or set of
     systems at once rather than individually. This allows administrators to
     be certain that similar systems are monitored in the same way and saves
     time configuring individual probes.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Notification Filters — Probe notifications may be redirected to
     another recipient, halted, or sent to an additional recipient for a
     specified time based on probe criteria, notification method, scout or
     organization.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="s1-automatic-notifications">
  <title>Patch Notifications and Scheduled Package Installations</title><indexterm>

  <primary>package installation</primary>

  <secondary>automatic updates</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>package installation</primary>

  <secondary>scheduled</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   You can configure &susemgr; to send you email notifications of new and
   updated software packages as soon as the packages are available through
   &ncc;. You receive one email per patch, regardless of the number of
   affected systems. You can also schedule package installs or package
   updates. The benefits include:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Reduced time and effort required by system administrators to stay on
     top of the patches list.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Minimized security vulnerabilities in your network through the
     application of updates as soon as &suse; releases them.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Filtered list of package updates (packages not relevant to your network
     are not included).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Reliable method of managing multiple systems with similar
     configurations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 id="s1-security-note">
  <title>Security, Quality Assurance, and &susemgr;</title><indexterm>

  <primary>Digital Certificate</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>GNU Privacy Guard</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>quality assurance</primary>

  <secondary>overview</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>Secure Sockets Layer</primary></indexterm><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>overview</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   &susemgr; provides significant benefits to your network, including
   security and quality assurance. All transactions between your
   systems and &susemgr; are encrypted and all RPM packages are signed with
   GNU Privacy Guard (GPG) signature to ensure authenticity.
  </para>

  <para>
   &susemgr; incorporates the following security measures:
  </para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Your system profile, available at &ncc;
     <ulink url="http://novell.com/center"/> is accessible only with a
     username and password.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     A digital certificate is written to the client system after
     registration and is used to authenticate the system during each
     transaction between the client and &susemgr;. The file is only readable
     by the root user on the client system.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &suse; signs all communications with an electronic signature using GPG.
     RPM can verify the authenticity of the package before it is
     installed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &suse; encrypts all transactions using a secure sockets layer (SSL)
     connection.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     The &suse; quality assurance team tests and verifies all packages
     before they are added to the patch list and &ncc;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
