<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>

<!DOCTYPE article [
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
 <?suse-quickstart color="suse"?>
 <title>&susemgr; in the Public Cloud</title>
 <subtitle>&susemgr; Server and &susemgr; Proxy in the Public
  Cloud</subtitle>
 <info>
  <productnumber><phrase>3</phrase></productnumber>
  <productname>&susemgr;</productname>
  <date>
   <?dbtimestamp format="B d, Y" ?></date>
  <abstract>
   <para> &susemgr; delivers best-in-class Linux server management
    capabilities. For detailed information about the product please refer to
    the <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/suse_manager">SUSE
     Manager</link> documentation. </para>
   <para> The &susemgr; Server and &susemgr; Proxy images published by
    SUSE in selected Public Cloud environments are provided as Bring Your Own
    Subscription (BYOS) images. &susemgr; Server instances need to be
    registered with the SUSE Customer Center (SCC). Subscriptions of
    &susemgr; Proxy instances are handled through their parent &susemgr;
    Server. After an instance is launched, &susemgr; needs to be set up and
    configured following the procedure in the &susemgr; documentation. </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>

 <sect1 xml:id="instance-requirements">
  <title>Instance Requirements</title>
  <para> Select an instance size that meets the system requirements as
   documented in the &susemgr; documentation. </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para> Minimal main memory: &gt;12G </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>The &susemgr; setup procedure performs a Forward-confirmed
     reverse DNS lookup. This must succeed in order for the setup procedure to
     complete successfully and for &susemgr; to operate as expected. Therefore
     it is important that the hostname and IP configuration be performed prior
     to running the &susemgr; setup procedure.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>&susemgr; Server and &susemgr; Proxy instances are expected
     to run in a network configuration that provides you control over
     DNS entries and that is shielded from the Internet at large. Within
     this network configuration DNS (Domain Name Service) resolution
     must be provided, such that <literal>hostname -f</literal> returns
     the FQDN (Full Qualified Domain Name). The DNS resolution is not only
     important for the &susemgr; Server procedure but is also important
     when clients are configured to be managed via &susemgr;. Configuring
     DNS is Cloud Framework dependent, please refer to the cloud service
     provider documentation for detailed instructions.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
     <para> Minimal free disk space for &susemgr; 15G.</para>
     <para>For Public Cloud instances we recommend that the repositories
     and the &susemgr; Server database, and respectively the &susemgr; Proxy
     squid cache, be located on an external virtual disk. The details for
     this setup are provided in
     <xref linkend="using-separate-storage-volume"/>. </para>
    <para> Storing the database and the repositories on an external virtual
     disk ensures that the data is not lost should the instance need to be
     terminated for some reason. </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para> Please ensure that the selected instance type matches the requirements
   listed above. Although we recommend that the database and the repositories
   are stored on a separate device it is still recommended to set the root
   volume size of the instance to 20G. </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="setup">
  <title>Setup</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Run an instance of the &susemgr; Server or &susemgr; Proxy
     image as published by SUSE. </para>
    <para> The images are identifiable by the suse, manager, server or proxy,
     and byos keywords in each public cloud environment. </para>
    <para> The &susemgr; instance must run in a network access restricted
     environment such as the private subnet of a VPC or with an appropriate
     firewall setting such that it can only be accessed by machines in the IP
     ranges you use. A generally accessible &susemgr; instance violates the
     terms of the &susemgr; EULA. Access to the web interface of SUSE
     Manager requires https. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Setup the hostname as follows: </para>

    <para> &susemgr; requires a stable and reliable hostname and does not
     take kindly to hostname changes. All commands provided need to be
     executed as the <emphasis role="strong">root</emphasis> user.</para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para> Disable hostname setup in the dhcp configuration file:
        <filename>/etc/sysconfig/network/dhcp</filename>
      </para>
      <screen>DHCLIENT_SET_HOSTNAME="no"</screen>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para> Set the hostname to a name of your choice. Please note
       it is important to provide the <replaceable>system name</replaceable>
       and not the <replaceable>fully qualified hostname</replaceable>
       to the <filename>hostnamectl</filename> command.</para>

       <para>It is expected that the Fully Qualified Domain Name (FQDN) is
       set by the cloud framework; for example if 
       <emphasis role="strong">cloud_instance.cloud.net</emphasis> is the
       fully qualified name than
       <emphasis role="strong">cloud_instance</emphasis>
       is the system name and <emphasis role="strong">cloud.net</emphasis>
       is the domain name.</para>

       <para>In the following example we will change the system name to
       <emphasis role="strong">suma</emphasis></para>
       <screen>$ hostnamectl set-hostname suma</screen>
       <para>The fully qualified hostname is now locally set to
       <emphasis role="strong">suma.cloud.net</emphasis>. Once the hostname
       is set locally a DNS entry needs to be created in your network
       environment such that domain name resolution works properly.</para>

       <para>Alternatively to force proper resolution of the name on the
       &susemgr; system you may alter the <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>
       file as follows:</para>
       <screen>$ echo "${local_address} suma.cloud.net suma" >> /etc/hosts</screen>
       <para>The current value for the <replaceable>local_address</replaceable>,
       can be obtained from the public cloud Web console or from within
       a terminal session as follows:</para>
       <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para> Obtain local ip address from within Amazon EC2 instance </para>
        <screen>$ ec2metadata --local-ipv4</screen>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para> Obtain local ip address from within Google Compute Engine instance </para>
        <screen>$ gcemetadata --query instance --network-interfaces --ip</screen>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para> Obtain local ip address from within Microsoft Azure instance </para>
        <screen>$ azuremetadata --internal-ip</screen>
       </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>

       <para>Note that forcing the DNS resolution to work via modification
       of the <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file will allow the
       <filename>yast2 susemanager_setup</filename> procedure to work. However,
       if DNS resolution is not properly configured this also implies that
       any client that is to be managed via this &susemgr; instance must
       also receive the same modification to <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>.
       </para>

       <para>One more aspect of hostname resolution is the
       <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename> file. Depending on the order of
       your setup, i.e. if you started the &susemgr; instance prior to setting
       up DNS services the file may not contain the appropriate
       <emphasis role="strong">search</emphasis> directive. Double check
       that the proper search directive exists in
       <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>. In our example the directive
       would be <emphasis role="strong">search cloud.net</emphasis>. If the
       directive is missing add it to the file.
       </para>

       <para>Reference information for the DNS record update is provided
       below.</para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
       <para>For an update of the DNS records for the instance within the
       DNS service of your network environment, refer to the cloud service
       provider documentation for detailed instructions:</para>
       <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para><link
         xlink:href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonVPC/latest/UserGuide/vpc-dns.html">
         DNS setup on Amazon EC2</link></para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para><link
         xlink:href="https://cloud.google.com/compute/docs/networking">
         DNS setup on Google Compute Engine</link></para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para><link
         xlink:href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/documentation/articles/dns-operations-recordsets">
         DNS setup on Microsoft Azure</link></para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Configure &susemgr; </para>
    <substeps performance="required">
     <step>
       <para> If you run a &susemgr; Server instance run YaST as shown
       below after the instance is launched, the external storage is
       attached and prepared according to
       <xref linkend="using-separate-storage-volume"/>, and the DNS resolution
       is set up as described earlier.</para>
       <screen>$ /sbin/yast2 susemanager_setup</screen>
       <para>Note that the setup of &susemgr; from this point forward does
       not differ from the documentation in the <link
        xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/suse_manager">SUSE
        Manager Guide</link>. </para>
      <para>The &susemgr; setup procedure in YaST is designed as a one pass
       process with no rollback or cleanup capability. Therefore, if the
       setup procedure is interrupted or ends with an error, it is not
       recommended to attempt a recovery as a reapate of the setup process or
       attempts to manually "fix" the configuration are most likely to fail
       and result in a broken &susemgr; installation. In case of any
       errors we recommend to start a new instance in order to run a
       fresh setup procedure on a clean system.
      </para>
      <para> If you are prompted with a message that there is not enough space
       available for the setup of &susemgr; verify that your root volume is
       at least 20GB and double check that the instructions in <xref
        linkend="using-separate-storage-volume"/> had the desired effects. </para>
      <para> &susemgr; Server for the Public Cloud comes with a bootstrap
       data module pre-installed that contains optimized package lists for
       bootstrapping instances started from SUSE Linux Enterprise images
       published by SUSE. If you intend to register such an instance,
       make sure when creating the bootstrap repository you run the
       mgr-create-bootstrap-repo script as follows:
      </para>
      <screen>$ mgr-create-bootstrap-repo --datamodule=mgr_pubcloud_bootstrap_data -c SLE-12-SP1-x86_64</screen>
      <para> The above example creates a bootstrap repository suitable for SUSE
       Linux Enterprise Server 12 SP1 instances. See <link
       xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/suse-manager-3/book.suma.getting-started/data/create_tools_repository.html">
       Creating the SUSE Manger Tools Repository</link> for more information on bootstrapping.
      </para>
      <para>Prior to registering instances started from on demand images
        remove the following packages from the instance to be registered:</para>
        <orderedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>cloud-regionsrv-client</para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para><emphasis role="strong">For Amazon EC2</emphasis></para>
             <para>regionServiceClientConfigEC2</para>
             <para>regionServiceCertsEC2</para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para><emphasis role="strong">For Google Compute Engine</emphasis></para>
             <para>cloud-regionsrv-client-plugin-gce</para>
             <para>regionServiceClientConfigGCE</para>
             <para>regionServiceCertsGCE</para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para><emphasis role="strong">For Microsoft Azure</emphasis></para>
             <para>regionServiceClientConfigAzure</para>
             <para>regionServiceCertsAzure</para>
           </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>If these packages are not removed it is possible to create interference
        between the repositories provided by &susemgr; and the repositories
        provided by the SUSE operated update infrastructure.
      </para>
      <para>Additionally remove the line from the
      <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file that contains the
      <emphasis role="strong">susecloud.net</emphasis> reference.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para> If you run a &susemgr; Proxy instance </para>
      <para> Launch the instance, optionally with external storage configured.
      If you use external storage (recommended), prepare it according to
      <xref linkend="using-separate-storage-volume"/>. It is recommended but
      not required to prepare the storage before configuring &susemgr; proxy,
      as the suma-storage script will migrate any existing cached data to the
      external storage. After preparing the instance, register the system
      with the parent SUSE Manager, which could be a &susemgr; Server or
      another &susemgr; Proxy. See the <link
        xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/documentation/suse-manager-3/singlehtml/suse_manager21/book_susemanager_proxyquick/book_susemanager_proxyquick.html"
        > &susemgr; Proxy Setup guide</link> for details. Once registered,
       run </para>
      <screen>$ /usr/sbin/configure-proxy.sh</screen>
      <para> to configure your &susemgr; Proxy instance. </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> After the completion of the configuration step, &susemgr; should
     be functional and running. For &susemgr; Server, the setup process
     created an administrator user with following user name: </para>
    <simplelist>
     <member>User name: <literal>admin</literal></member>
    </simplelist>
    <table>
     <title>Account credentials for admin user</title>
     <tgroup cols="3">
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para> Amazon EC2 </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para> Google Compute Engine </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para> Microsoft Azure </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <replaceable>Instance-ID</replaceable>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <replaceable>Instance-ID</replaceable>
         </para>
        </entry>
        <entry>
         <para>
          <replaceable>Instance-Name</replaceable><emphasis role="strong"
           >-suma</emphasis>
         </para>
        </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para> The current value for the <replaceable>Instance-ID</replaceable> or
      <replaceable>Instance-Name</replaceable> in case of the Azure Cloud, can
     be obtained from the public cloud Web console or from within a terminal
     session as follows: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para> Obtain instance id from within Amazon EC2 instance </para>
      <screen>$ ec2metadata --instance-id</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para> Obtain instance id from within Google Compute Engine instance </para>
      <screen>$ gcemetadata --query instance --id</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para> Obtain instance name from within Microsoft Azure instance </para>
      <screen>$ azuremetadata --instance-name</screen>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para> After logging in through the &susemgr; Server Web UI, <emphasis
      role="strong">change</emphasis> the default password. </para>
    <para> &susemgr; Proxy does not have administration Web interface
     itself. It can be managed through its parent &susemgr; Server. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <sect2 xml:id="using-separate-storage-volume">
   <title>Using Separate Storage Volume</title>
   <para> We recommend that the repositories and the database for &susemgr;
    be stored on a virtual storage device. This best practice will avoid data
    loss in cases where the &susemgr; instance may need to be terminated.
    These steps <emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> be performed <emphasis
     role="strong">prior</emphasis> to running the YaST &susemgr; setup
    procedure. </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para> Provision a disk device in the public cloud environment, refer to
      the cloud service provider documentation for detailed instructions. The
      size of the disk is dependent on the number of distributions and channels
      you intend to manage with &susemgr;. For sizing information refer to
       <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/kb/doc.php?id=7015050"
       >&susemgr; sizing examples</link>. A rule of thumb is 25 GB per
      distribution per channel. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Once attached the device appears as Unix device node in your
      instance. For the following command to work this device node name is
      required. In many cases the attached storage appears as <emphasis
       role="strong">/dev/sdb</emphasis>. In order to check which disk devices
      exists on your system, call the following command: </para>
     <screen>$ hwinfo --disk | grep -E "Device File:"</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> With the device name at hand the process of re-linking the
      directories in the filesystem &susemgr; uses to store data is handled
      by the suma-storage script. In the following example we use
       <filename>/dev/sdb</filename> as the device name. </para>
     <screen>$ /usr/bin/suma-storage /dev/sdb</screen>
     <para> After the call all database and repository files used by SUSE
      Manager Server are moved to the newly created xfs based storage. In case
      your instance is a &susemgr; Proxy, the script will move the Squid
      cache, which caches the software packages, to the newly created storage.
      The xfs partition is mounted below the path
       <filename>/manager_storage</filename>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Create an entry in /etc/fstab (optional) </para>
     <para> Different cloud frameworks treat the attachment of external storage
      devices differently at instance boot time. Please refer to the cloud
      environment documentation for guidance about the fstab entry. </para>
     <para> If your cloud framework recommends to add an fstab entry, add the
      following line to the <emphasis role="strong">/etc/fstab</emphasis> file. </para>
     <screen>/dev/sdb1 /manager_storage xfs defaults 1 1</screen>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="registration-of-cloned-systems">
  <title>Registration of Cloned Systems</title>
  <para> &susemgr; treats systems (instances) with the same system ID as one.
   This implies that one instance will mask another if the instances have the
   same system ID. This situation occurs by launching multiple instances from
   the same image or when an image has been created from a running instance.
   Thus prior to registering a new instance complete step 5.1 or 5.2, 
   depending on the distribution on the following wiki.</para>
  <para>
   <link
    xlink:href="http://wiki.novell.com/index.php/SUSE_Manager/Register_Clones"
   />
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
