<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ref.webui.salt">
 <title>Salt</title>
<!-- index --><indexterm>
 <primary>Web Interface</primary>
 <secondary>Salt</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Open the <guimenu>Salt</guimenu> menu on the left bar.
  <guimenu>Keys</guimenu> provides an overview of your Salt minions
  (clients). Use
<!-- <guimenu>Bootstrapping</guimenu> to bootstrap
 systems remotely or -->
  <guimenu>Remote Commands</guimenu> to execute remote commands on your Salt
  minions. You can also define a <guimenu>State Catalog</guimenu> for creating
  a collection of salt system states.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.salt.onboarding">
  <title>Keys</title>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>Keys</guimenu> page provides a summary of your minions,
   including their names, fingerprints, state, and actions you may
   perform on them.
  </para>

  <para>
   Once you have pointed a minion to the &susemgr; server as its master within
   <replaceable>/etc/salt/minion</replaceable>, you can choose to accept or
   reject a minion from this page.  Either click the check mark or cross
   in the actions column.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Keys Overview</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="onboarding.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="onboarding.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   For more information about key handling and onboarding, see
   <xref
    linkend="preparing.and.registering.clients.salt"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.salt.remote.commands">
  <title>Remote Commands</title>

<!-- Update the images for running a remote command and add script to fennek -->

  <para>
   The remote commands page allows you to execute and run commands from the
   &susemgr; server on several minions.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>Remote Commands</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="remote_commands.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="remote_commands.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <warning>
   <title>Remote Commands Security</title>
   <para>
    All commands run from the <guimenu>Remote Commands</guimenu> page are
    executed as &rootuser; on minions. As you may use wildcards to run commands
    across any number of systems you must always take extra precaution as this
    may have drastic consequences for your systems.
   </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
   On the <guimenu>Remote Commands</guimenu> page located under
   <menuchoice> <guimenu>Salt</guimenu> <guimenu>Remote Commands</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> you will see two text boxes. The first box is for entering
   commands. The second box is for targeting minions by name, group or by
   using wildcards.
  </para>

  <para>
   Input a command you want to execute, add a target minion, group or wildcard
   you want to execute the command on. Select the <guimenu>Find
   Targets</guimenu> button to verify which machines will be targeted. Select
   the <guimenu>Run Command</guimenu> button to execute a command on selected
   systems.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.salt.states.catalog">
  <title>State Catalog</title>

  <para>
   Selecting <menuchoice> <guimenu>Salt</guimenu> <guimenu>State
   Catalog</guimenu> </menuchoice> presents you with the <guimenu>State
   Catalog</guimenu> overview. You can use this page to manage custom Salt
   states. Salt states created on this page may be applied to organizations,
   groups, and single systems.
  </para>

  <figure>
   <title>State Catalog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="state_catalog.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="state_catalog.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

<!--Add script to fennek for creating a state with example -->

  <para>
   Click the <guimenu>Create State</guimenu> button to open the <guimenu>Create
   State</guimenu> page. On this page you can define custom states which will
   be stored within the <guimenu>State Catalog</guimenu>. For example, to
   create a custom state for installation of the apache Web server you would
   provide a name: <guimenu>Webserver</guimenu> and the state content:
  </para>

<screen>apache:
  pkg.installed: []
  service.running:
    - require:
      - pkg: apache</screen>

  <para>
   When you have finished entering your custom state definition click the
   <guimenu>Create State</guimenu> button. This will save the state and allow
   use of this specific state at the minion, group, and organization level.
  </para>

  <para>
   To add this state at the individual minion level perform the following
   actions:
  </para>

  <procedure>
   <title>Using a State with a Minion</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     From the <guimenu>Systems</guimenu> overview page, select a salt managed
     minion. You will be taken to the <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select <menuchoice> <guimenu>States</guimenu> <guimenu>Custom</guimenu>
     </menuchoice> from the navigation tabs.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the search button to look at an overview of all available states, or
     enter a custom state name to find it within the <guimenu>State
     Catalog</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the <guimenu>Assign</guimenu> check box to assign the state to this
     minion.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guimenu>Save</guimenu> button to save this assignment to the
     database. Then click the <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> button to finalize
     application of the state or states which you have selected.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <note>
   <title>The Save Button</title>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Save</guimenu> button saves your changes but does not apply
    the state. If you leave the page after clicking the save button your state
    will be saved to the database but not yet applied. You must apply states
    for all minions, groups, or organizations for states to be finalized.
   </para>
  </note>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
