<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>


<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>

<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ref.webui.salt">

    <title>Salt</title>

    <!-- index -->
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Web Interface</primary>
        <secondary>Salt</secondary></indexterm>
    <para> If you click the <guimenu>Salt</guimenu> tab on the top navigation bar, by default the <menuchoice>
            <guimenu>Salt</guimenu>
            <guimenu>Onboarding</guimenu>
        </menuchoice> view appears. On the left sidebar you can select <guimenu>Remote
            Commands</guimenu> to execute remote commands on your Salt Minions. You may also define
        a <guimenu>States Catalog</guimenu> for creating a collection of salt system states. </para>

    <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.salt.onboarding">
        <title>Onboarding</title>
        <para> The <guimenu>Onboarding</guimenu> page provides a summary of your minions, including
            their names, fingerprints, current state, and actions you may perform on them. </para>

        <para>Once you have pointed a minion to the &susemgr; server as its master within
                <replaceable>/etc/salt/minion</replaceable>, you can choose to accept or reject a
            minion from this page.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>Onboarding Overview</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="onboarding-overview.png" width="444"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="onboarding-overview.png" width="80%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>


    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.salt.remote.commands">
        <title>Remote Commands</title>
        <para>The remote commands page allows you to execute and run commands from the &susemgr;
            server on minions. </para>
        <warning>
            <title>Remote Commands Security</title>
            <para>All commands run from the <literal>Remote Commands</literal> page are executed as
                root on minions. As you may use wildcards to run commands across any number of
                systems you must always take extra precaution as this may have drastic consequences
                for your systems.</para>
        </warning>

        <para>From the <literal>Remote Commands</literal> page within located under <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Salt</guimenu>
                <guimenu>Remote Commands</guimenu>
            </menuchoice> you will see two input fields. The first field is for entering commands.
            The second field is for targeting minions by name, group or by utilizing
            wildcards.</para>

        <para>Enter the command you wish to execute, then enter the minion, group or wildcard you
            wish to execute the command on. Click the <literal>Preview</literal> button to see which
            machines will be targeted. Click the <literal>Run</literal> button to execute a command
            on the previewed systems. </para>
        <note>
            <title>Previewing Target Systems</title>
            <para>The <guibutton>Preview</guibutton> button should always be selected before the
                    <guibutton>Run</guibutton> button. Systems you wish to run a command on must be
                available as a target.</para>
        </note>
        <figure>
            <title>Remote Commands</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="remote-commands.png" width="444"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="remote-commands.png" width="80%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

    </sect1>

    <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.salt.states.catalog">
        <title>States Catalog</title>
        <para>Selecting <menuchoice>
                <guimenu>Salt</guimenu>
                <guimenu>States Catalog</guimenu>
            </menuchoice> brings you to the <literal>States Catalog</literal> overview. Use this
            page to manage your custom Salt states. </para>
        <figure>
            <title>States Catalog</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject role="fo">
                    <imagedata fileref="states-catalog.png" width="444"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject role="html">
                    <imagedata fileref="states-catalog.png" width="80%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>Click the <literal>+ Create State</literal> button to open the <literal>Create
                State</literal> page. On this page you can define custom states which will be stored
            within the <literal>State Catalog</literal>. For example, to create a custom state for
            installation of the apache webserver you would provide a name:
                <literal>Webserver</literal> and the state content:</para>

        <screen>apache:
  pkg.installed: []
  service.running:
    - require:
      - pkg: apache</screen>

        <para>When you have finished entering your custom state definition click the <literal>Create
                State</literal> button. This will save the state and allow use of this specific
            state at the minion, group and organization level.</para>

        <para>To add this state at the individual minion level perform the following actions:</para>
        <procedure>
            <title>Using a State with a Minion</title>
            <step>
                <para>From the <guimenu>Systems</guimenu> overview page, select a salt managed
                    minion. You will be taken to the <literal>System Details</literal> page.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para> Select <menuchoice>
                        <guimenu>States</guimenu>
                        <guimenu>Custom</guimenu>
                    </menuchoice> from the navigation tabs.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Click the search button to look at an overview of all available states, or
                    enter a custom state name to find it within the <literal>States
                        Catalog</literal>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Select the <literal>Assign</literal> checkbox to assign the state to this
                    minion.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Click the <literal>Save</literal> button to save this assignment to the
                    database. Then click the <literal>Apply</literal> button to finalize application
                    of the state or states which you have selected.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>
        <note>
            <title>The Save Button</title>
            <para>The <literal>Save</literal> button saves your changes but does not apply the
                state. If you leave the page once clicking the save button your state will be saved
                to the database but not yet applied. You must apply states for all minions, groups
                or organizations for states to be finalized.</para>
        </note>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
