<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!-- z: s1-sm-your-rhn ref.webui xxx -->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="ref.webui">
 <title>Web Interface &mdash; Navigation and Overview</title>
 <info>
  <abstract>
   <para> This is a chapter about the layout of the Web Interface to &susemgr; and basic usage
    information. </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>

 <!-- -=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=- cut here -=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=- -->
 <xi:include href="reference-webui-intro.xml" parse="xml"/>
 <!-- -=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=- cut here -=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=-=- -->

 <!-- z: s1-sm-your-rhn-overview ref.webui.overview s1-sm-your-rhn -->
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.overview">
  <title>Overview</title>
  <!--idx-->
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Overview</primary>
   <secondary>Web interface</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para> Entering the &susemgr; URL in a browser takes you to the <guimenu>Sign in</guimenu> screen.
   If you click on the <guimenu>About</guimenu> tab before logging in, you will find documentation
   links, including a search function, and the option to request your login credentials if you
   forgot either password or login. Click on <guimenu>Lookup Login/Password</guimenu>. For more
   information, see <xref linkend="ref.webui.overview.account"/>. </para>
  <para> After logging into the Web interface of &susemgr;, the first page to appear is
    <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>. This page contains important information about your systems,
   including summaries of system status, actions, and patch alerts. </para>

  <note>
   <para> If you are new to the &susemgr; Web interface, read <xref linkend="ref.webui.intro"/> to
    familiarize yourself with the layout and symbols used throughout the interface. </para>
  </note>

  <figure>
   <title>Overview</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="webui-overview.png" width="400"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="webui-overview.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para> This page is split into functional sections, with the most critical sections displayed
   first. Users can control which of the following sections are displayed by making selections on
   the <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Your Preferences</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> page. Refer to <xref linkend="ref.webui.overview.prefs"/> for more information. </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para> The <guimenu>Tasks</guimenu> section lists the most common tasks an administrator
     performs via the Web interface. Click any link to reach the page within &susemgr; that allows
     you to accomplish that task. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> If any systems have not been checking in to &susemgr;, they are listed under
      <guimenu>Inactive System</guimenu> to the right. Highlighting them in this way allows an
     administrator to quickly select those systems for troubleshooting. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> The <guimenu>Most Critical Systems</guimenu> section lists the most critical systems
     within your organization. It provides a link to quickly view those systems and displays a
     summary of the patch updates that have yet to be applied to those systems. Click the name of
     the system to see its <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page and apply the patch updates.
     <!-- ke, 2011-03-23: Never saw this 'out of date' page.
    But 'Systems' > 'Systems' features such a page.
    Now here we have 'View All Critical Systems'
-->
     Below the list is a link to <guimenu>View All Critical Systems</guimenu> on one page.
     <!-- 'out of date' systems
    have applicable patch alerts that have not been applied.
-->
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> The <guimenu>Recently Scheduled Actions</guimenu> section lists all actions less than
     thirty days old and their status: failed, completed, or pending. Click the label of any given
     action to view its details page. Below the list is a link to <guimenu>View All Scheduled
      Actions</guimenu> on one page, which lists all actions that have not yet been carried out on
     your client systems. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> The <guimenu>Relevant Security Patches</guimenu> section lists all available security
     patches that have yet to be applied to some or all of your client systems. It is critical that
     you apply these security patches to keep your systems secure. Below this list find links to all
     patches (<guimenu>View All Patches</guimenu>) and to the patches that apply to your systems
      (<guimenu>View All Relevant Patches</guimenu>). </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> The <guimenu>System Group Names</guimenu> section lists groups you may have created and
     indicates whether the systems in those groups are fully updated. Click the link below this
     section to get to the <guimenu>System Groups</guimenu> page, where you can choose
      <guimenu>System Groups</guimenu> to use with the System Set Manager. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> The <guimenu>Recently Registered Systems</guimenu> section lists the systems added to the
     &susemgr; in the past 30 days. Click a system's name to see its <guimenu>System
      Details</guimenu> page. Click the link below this section to <guimenu>View All Recently
      Registered Systems</guimenu> on one page. </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para> To return to this page, click <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> on the left navigation bar.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <!-- z: s2-sm-your-rhn-account ref.webui.overview.account -->
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.account">
  <title>Your Account</title>
  <!-- idx -->
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Oracle</primary>
   <secondary>Your Account</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>WebLogic</primary>
   <secondary>Your Account</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para> On the <guimenu>Your Account</guimenu> page modify your personal information, such as name,
   password, and title. To modify any of this information, make the changes in the appropriate text
   fields and click the <guimenu>Update</guimenu> button at the bottom. </para>

  <para> If you change your &susemgr; password, for security reasons you will not see the new
   password while you enter it. Replace the asterisks in the <guimenu>Password</guimenu> and
    <guimenu>Confirm Password</guimenu> text fields with the new password. </para>
  <note>
   <para> Should you forget your password or username, go to the login screen and click the
     <guimenu>About</guimenu> tab, then select the <guimenu>Lookup Login/Password</guimenu> page.
    Here you can either specify your login and email address or only your email address if you are
    not sure about the username. Then click on <guimenu>Send Password</guimenu> or <guimenu>Send
     Login</guimenu> respectively. </para>
  </note>
  <!-- z: s3-sm-your-rhn-address ref.webui.overview.account.addresses -->
  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.account.addresses">
   <title>Addresses</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>account</primary>
    <secondary>change</secondary></indexterm>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>Oracle</primary>
    <secondary>Addresses</secondary></indexterm>
   <para> On the <guimenu>Addresses</guimenu> page manage your mailing, billing and shipping
    addresses, and the associated phone numbers. Click <guimenu>Edit this address</guimenu> below
    the address to be modified, make the changes, and click <guimenu>Update</guimenu>. </para>
  </sect2>

  <!-- z: s3-sm-your-rhn-email ref.webui.overview.account.email -->
  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.account.email">
   <title>Change Email</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>email address</primary>
    <secondary>change</secondary></indexterm>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>Oracle</primary>
    <secondary>Email</secondary></indexterm>
   <para> The email address listed in the <guimenu>Your Account</guimenu> page is the address to
    which &susemgr; sends email notifications if you select to receive patch alerts or daily
    summaries for your systems on the <guimenu>Your Preferences</guimenu> page. </para>
   <para> To change your preferred email address, click <guimenu>Change Email</guimenu> in the left
    navigation bar. Enter your new email address and click the <guimenu>Update</guimenu> button. <!-- 2016-05-23: no confirmation mail; bsc#979491 -->
    <!-- A confirmation email is -->
    <!-- sent to the new email address; responding to the confirmation email -->
    <!-- validates the new email address. --> Invalid email addresses like those ending in
     <literal>@localhost</literal> are filtered and rejected. </para>
  </sect2>

  <!-- z: s3-sm-your-rhn-credentials ref.webui.overview.account.credentials -->
  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.account.credentials">
   <title>Credentials</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>account</primary>
    <secondary>credentials</secondary></indexterm>
   <para> View or enter external system or API credentials associated with your &susemgr; account,
    for example your &suse; Studio credentials. </para>
  </sect2>

  <!-- z: s3-sm-your-rhn-deactivate ref.webui.overview.account.deactivate -->
  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.account.deactivate">
   <title>Account Deactivation</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>account</primary>
    <secondary>deactivate</secondary></indexterm>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>Oracle</primary>
    <secondary>Account Deactivation</secondary></indexterm>
   <para> The <guimenu>Account Deactivation</guimenu> page provides a means to cancel your &susemgr;
    service. To do so, click the <guimenu>Deactivate Account</guimenu> button. The Web interface
    returns you to the login screen. If you attempt to log back in, an error message advises you to
    contact the &susemgr; administrator for your organization. Note that if you are the only
    &susemgr; Administrator for your organization, you are unable to deactivate your account.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <!-- z: s2-sm-your-rhn-prefs ref.webui.overview.prefs -->
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.prefs">
  <title>Your Preferences</title>
  <!-- idx -->
  <indexterm>
   <primary>WebUI</primary>
   <secondary>Your Preferences</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para> The <guimenu>Your Preferences</guimenu> page allows you to configure &susemgr; options,
   including: </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Email Notifications</guimenu> — Determine whether you want to receive email every time
     a patch alert is applicable to one or more systems in your account. </para>
    <important>
     <para> This setting also enables Management and Provisioning customers to receive a daily
      summary of system events. These include actions affecting packages, such as scheduled patches,
      system reboots, or failures to check in. In addition to selecting this check box, you must
      identify each system to be included in this summary email. By default, all Management and
      Provisioning systems are included in the summary. Add more systems either individually on the
       <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page or for multiple systems at once in the <guimenu>System
       Set Manager</guimenu> interface. Note that &susemgr; sends these summaries only to verified
      email addresses. To disable all messages, simply deselect this check box. </para>
    </important>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>&susemgr; List Page Size</guimenu> — Maximum number of items that appear in a list on
     a single page. If more items are in the list, clicking the <guimenu>Next</guimenu> button
     displays the next group of items. This preference applies to system lists, patch lists, package
     lists, and so on. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>&quot;Overview&quot; Start Page</guimenu> — Select the information sections that are
     displayed on the <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> Start Page. Check the box to the left of the
     information section you would like to include. </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>CSV Files</guimenu> — Select the separator character to be used in downloadable CSV
     files. <guimenu>Comma</guimenu> is the default; as an alternative use
      <guimenu>Semicolon</guimenu>, which is more compatible with Microsoft Excel. </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para> After making changes to any of these options, click the <guimenu>Save Preferences</guimenu>
   button. </para>
 </sect1>
 <!-- z: s2-yourrhn-locale ref.webui.overview.locale -->
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.locale">
  <title>Locale Preferences</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>package installation</primary>
   <secondary>language</secondary></indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>package installation</primary>
   <secondary>locale</secondary></indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>WebLogic</primary>
   <secondary>language</secondary></indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>WebLogic</primary>
   <secondary>locale</secondary></indexterm>

  <para> On the <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Locale Preferences</guimenu>
   </menuchoice> page set your &susemgr; interface to your local time by selecting the appropriate
    <guimenu>Time Zone</guimenu> from the drop-down box, then click the <guimenu>Save
    Preferences</guimenu> button to apply the selection. </para>

  <!-- FIXME: ATM, language selection is disabled
   <para>
    Select your preferred language. When the language preference is set
    to <guilabel>Use Browser Settings</guilabel>, &susemgr; uses the language
    preference from the user's browser (such
    as <application>Firefox</application>) to determine which language to use
    for the Web interface. When one of the listed languages is selected, the
    user sees the web interface in that language each time they log in,
    regardless of their browser's settings. Choosing a preferred language may
    be helpful for users traveling abroad. To select a default language, click
    the radio button to the left of the appropriate language and click
    the <guibutton>Save Preferences</guibutton> button to apply the change.
   </para>
  -->
 </sect1>
 <!-- z: == ref.webui.overview.org -->
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.org">
  <title>Your Organization</title>
  <para> From the <guimenu>Your Organization</guimenu> page you can modify your organization's
    <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> and <guimenu>Organization Trusts</guimenu> and manage custom
   Salt states distributed across an organization. </para>

  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.org.config">
   <title>Configuration</title>
   <para> On the <guimenu>Configuration</guimenu> page modify your personal information, such as
    name, password, and title. To modify any of this information, make the changes in the
    appropriate text fields and click the <guimenu>Update</guimenu> button at the bottom. </para>
  </sect2>

  <!-- z: yourrhn-orgtrusts ref.webui.overview.org.trust -->
  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.org.trust">
   <title>Organization Trusts</title>

   <para> The <guimenu>Organization Trusts</guimenu> page displays the trusts established with your
    organization (that is, the organization with which you, the logged-in user, are associated). The
    page also lists <guimenu>Channels Shared</guimenu>, which refers to channels available to your
    organization via others in the established trusts. </para>

   <para> You can filter the list of trusts by keyword using the <guimenu>Filter by
     Organization</guimenu> text box and clicking <guimenu>Go</guimenu>. </para>

   <!-- <para> -->
   <!--  For more information about organizational trusts, refer to -->
   <!--  <xref linkend="s1-sattools-orgs-trust"/>. -->
   <!-- </para> -->
  </sect2>

  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.org.custom.states">
   <title>Custom States</title>
   <para>The <guimenu>Custom States</guimenu> page displays states which have been created and added
    using the <guimenu>Salt</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>State Catalog</guimenu>. From this page you can
    select which states should be applied across your organization. A state applied from this page
    will be applied to all minions within an organization.</para>
   <note>
    <para>Keep in mind states are applied according to the following order of hierarchy within SUSE
     Manager. <literal>Organization</literal> > <literal>Group</literal> > <literal>Single
      System</literal></para>
   </note>

   <procedure>
    <title>Apply a Custom State at the Organization Level</title>
    <step>
     <para>Create a state using the <guimenu>Salt</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>State Catalog</guimenu> or
      via the command line.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Browse to <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Your Organization</guimenu> &gt;
       <guimenu>Custom States</guimenu>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Use the search feature to located a state by name or click the <guimenu>Search</guimenu>
      button to list all available states.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the checkbox for the state to be applied and click the <guimenu>Save</guimenu>
      button. The save button will save the change to the database but will not apply the
      state.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Apply the state by clicking the <guimenu>Apply</guimenu> button. The state will be
      scheduled and applied to any systems included within the organization.</para>
    </step>
   </procedure>

  </sect2>
  <!-- <remark>Commenting out until this section has been completed.</remark>
  <sect2 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.org.custstates">
   <title>Custom States</title>
   

    <para>
    For more information about Custom States, see <xref
    linkend="bp.chapt.config.mgr.target.org.group.custom.states.using.pillars"/>.
  </para> 
  </sect2> -->

 </sect1>
 <!-- z: s2-sm-systems-entitlements ref.webui.overview.subscr.entitlem
  -->
 <!-- 
 <sect1 xml:id="ref.webui.overview.subscr.entitlem">
  <title>Subscription Management</title>
  <!-\- idx -\->
  <indexterm>
   <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

   <secondary>entitling</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

   <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

   <secondary>Entitlements</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

   <primary>WebLogic</primary>

   <secondary>System Entitlements</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   To use all of the features of &susemgr;, your systems must be entitled
   — subscribed to &ncc;. Use the <guimenu>System
   Entitlements</guimenu> page to configure which systems are entitled to
   which service offerings.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 -->
</chapter>
