<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="s1-sm-users">
 <title>Users — [Mgmt]</title>
 <info/><indexterm>
 <primary>users</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>WebLogic</primary>
 <secondary>Users</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  Only &susemgr; administrators can see the <guimenu>Users</guimenu> tab
  on the top navigation bar. If you click the tab, the
  <guimenu>Users</guimenu> category and links appear. Here you grant and
  edit permissions for those who administer your system groups. Click on a
  name in the <guimenu>User List</guimenu> to modify the user.
 </para>
 <para>
  To add new users to your organization, click the <guimenu>create new
  user</guimenu> link on the top right corner of the page. On the
  <guimenu>Create User</guimenu> page, fill in the required values for the
  new user.
 </para>
 <para>
  Once all fields are completed, click the <guimenu>Create Login</guimenu>
  button. &susemgr; now sends an email to the specified address and takes
  you back to the <menuchoice><guimenu>Users</guimenu><guimenu>User
  List</guimenu><guimenu>Active</guimenu></menuchoice> page. If you wish to
  set permissions and options for the new user, click on the name in the
  list. The <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> page for this user provides
  several subtabs of options. Refer to
  <xref linkend="s3-sm-user-active-details"/> for detailed descriptions of
  each subtab.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-user-active">
<!-- User List ⇒ Active —  [Mgmt]-->

  <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>

  <para>
   The user list shows all active users on your &susemgr; and displays
   basic information about each user: username, real name, roles, and date
   of their last sign in.
  </para>

  <para>
   As shown in <xref linkend="fig-users-fig"/>, each row in the
   <guimenu>User List</guimenu> represents a user within your organization.
   There are four columns of information for each user:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Username</guimenu> — The login name of the user. Clicking on
     a username, displays the <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> page for the
     user. Refer to <xref linkend="s3-sm-user-active-details"/> for more
     information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Real Name</guimenu> — The full name of the user (last name
     first).
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Roles</guimenu> — List of the user's privileges, such as
     organization administrator, channel administrator and normal user.
     Users can have multiple roles.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Last Sign In</guimenu> — Shows when the user last logged in
     to &susemgr;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <figure xml:id="fig-users-fig">
   <title>User List</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="user_list.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="user_list.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <sect2 xml:id="s3-sm-user-active-details">
   <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title><indexterm>
   <primary>deactivate</primary>
   <secondary>user</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>deactivate</primary>
   <secondary>user (&susemgr; only)</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    On the <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> page &susemgr;, administrators
    manage the permissions and activity of all users. Here you can also
    delete or deactivate users.
   </para>
   <para>
    Users can be deactivated directly in the &susemgr; Web interface.
    &susemgr; administrators can deactivate or delete users of their
    organization, but users can also deactivate their own accounts.
   </para>
   <para>
    Deactivated users cannot log in to the &susemgr; Web interface or
    schedule any actions. &susemgr; administrators cannot be deactivated
    until that role is removed from their account. Actions scheduled by a
    user prior to their deactivation remain in the action queue. Deactivated
    users can be reactivated by &susemgr; administrators.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <title>Irreversible Deletion</title>
    <para>
     User deletion is irreversible; exercise it with caution. Consider
     deactivating the user first in order to assess the effect deletion will
     have on your infrastructure.
    </para>
   </warning>
   <para>
    To deactivate a user:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click on a user name to navigate to the <guimenu>User
      Details</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Verify that the user is not a &susemgr; administrator. If they are,
      uncheck the box to the left of that role and click the
      <guimenu>Submit</guimenu> button.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>deactivate user</guimenu> link in the upper right
      of the screen.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Deactivate User</guimenu> button in the lower right
      to confirm.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    To delete a user:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click on a user name to navigate to the <guimenu>User
      Details</guimenu> tab.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Verify that the user is not a &susemgr; administrator. Uncheck the
      box to remove the role if necessary.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>delete user</guimenu> link in the upper right.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guimenu>Delete User</guimenu> button to permanently delete
      the user.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para>
    For instructions to deactivate your own account, refer to
    <xref linkend="s3-sm-your-rhn-deactivate"/>.
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-usr-active-details-details">
    <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Details</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title><indexterm>
    <primary>changing email address</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>changing password</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>email address</primary>
    <secondary>changing</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>&susemgr; administrator</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
    <primary>user roles</primary></indexterm>
    <para>
     This is the default <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> tab, which displays
     the username, first name, last name, email address, and roles of a
     user. Edit this information as needed and click
     <guimenu>Update</guimenu>. When changing a user's password, you will
     only see asterisks as you type.
    </para>
    <para>
     To delegate responsibilities within your organization, &susemgr;
     provides several roles with varying degrees of access. This list
     describes the permissions of each role and the differences between
     them:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>User</guimenu> — Also known as a <emphasis>System Group
       User</emphasis>, this is the standard role associated with any newly
       created user. This person may be granted access to manage system
       groups and software channels, if the &susemgr; administrator sets
       the roles accordingly. The systems must be in system groups for which
       the user has permissions to manage them. However, all globally
       subscribable channels may be used by anyone.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Activation Key Administrator</guimenu> — This role is
       designed to manage your collection of activation keys. A user
       assigned to this role can modify and delete any key within your
       organization.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Channel Administrator</guimenu> — This role provides a
       user with full access to all software channels within your
       organization. This requires the &susemgr; synchronization tool
       (<command>mgr-ncc-sync</command>). The channel administrator may
       change the base channels of systems, make channels globally
       subscribable, and create entirely new channels.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Organization Administrator</guimenu> — This role provides
       a user with all the permissions other administrators have, namely the
       activation key, configuration, monitoring, channel, and system group
       administrator.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Configuration Administrator</guimenu> — This role enables
       a user to manage the configuration of systems within the
       organization, using either the &susemgr; Web interface or the
       <systemitem>rhncfg-management</systemitem>.
       <remark>ke
       2011-03-29: was "&rhn; Configuration Manager"</remark>
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Monitoring Administrator</guimenu> — This role allows for
       the scheduling of probes and oversight of other monitoring
       infrastructure. This role is available only on a monitoring-enabled
       &susemgr; server. Activate monitoring in
       <menuchoice><guimenu>Admin</guimenu><guimenu>&susemgr;
       Configuration</guimenu><guimenu>General</guimenu></menuchoice> and
       click on <guimenu>Enable Monitoring</guimenu>. See
       <xref linkend="s1-sm-monitor"/> for more information.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>&susemgr; Administrator</guimenu> — This role allows a
       user to perform any function available in &susemgr;. As the master
       account for your organization, the person holding this role can alter
       the privileges of all other accounts, as well as conduct any of the
       tasks available to the other roles. Like with other roles, multiple
       &susemgr; administrators may exist. Go to
       <menuchoice><guimenu>Admin</guimenu><guimenu>Users</guimenu></menuchoice>
       and click the check box in the <guimenu>&susemgr; Admin?</guimenu>
       row. <guimenu>&susemgr; Administrator</guimenu> manages foreign
       organizations; for example, a <guimenu>&susemgr;
       Administrator</guimenu> can only create users for an organization if
       he is entitled with organization administrator privileges for this
       organization.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>System Group Administrator</guimenu> — This role is one
       step below &susemgr; administrator: full authority is limited to
       systems or system groups to which access is granted. The System Group
       Administrator can create new system groups, delete any assigned
       systems from groups, add systems to groups, and manage user access to
       groups.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Being a &susemgr; administrator enables you to remove administrator
     rights from other users. It is possible to remove your own privileges
     as long as you are not the only &susemgr; administrator.
    </para>
    <para>
     To assign a new role to a user, check the respective box. &susemgr;
     administrators are automatically granted administration access to all
     other roles, signified by grayed-out check boxes. Click
     <guimenu>Submit</guimenu> to submit your changes.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-usr-active-details-sysg">
    <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>System Groups</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>
    <para>
     This tab displays a list of system groups the user may administer.
     &susemgr; administrators can set this user's access permissions to
     each system group. Check or uncheck the box to the left of the system
     group and click the <guimenu>Update Permissions</guimenu> button to
     save the changes.
    </para>
    <para>
     &susemgr; administrators may select one or more default system
     groups for a user. When the user registers a system, it gets assigned
     to the selected group or groups. This allows the user to access the
     newly-registered system immediately. System groups to which this user
     has access are preceded by an (*).
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-usr-active-details-systems">
    <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Systems</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>
    <para>
     This tab lists all systems a user can access according to the system
     groups assigned to the user. To carry out tasks on some of these
     systems, select the set of systems by checking the boxes to the left
     and click the <guimenu>Update List</guimenu> button. Use the System Set
     Manager page to execute actions on those systems. Clicking the name of
     a system takes you to its <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page. Refer
     to <xref linkend="s3-sm-system-details"/> for more information.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-usr-active-details-chans">
    <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Channel Permissions</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>
    <para>
     This tab lists all channels available to your organization. Grant
     explicit channel subscription permission to a user for each of the
     channels listed by checking the box to the left of the channel, then
     click the <guimenu>Update Permissions</guimenu> button. Permissions
     granted by a &susemgr; administrator or channel administrator have
     no check box but a check icon just like globally subscribable channels.
    </para>
    <sect4 xml:id="s5-sm-user-details-chanperms-subs">
     <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Channel Permissions</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Subscription</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>
     <para>
      Identifies channels to which the user may subscribe systems. To change
      these, select or deselect the appropriate check boxes and click the
      <guimenu>Update Permissions</guimenu> button. Note that channels
      subscribable due to the user's administrator status or the channel's
      global settings cannot be altered. They are identified with a check
      icon.
     </para>
    </sect4>
    <sect4 xml:id="s5-sm-user-details-chanperms-mgmt">
     <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Channel Permissions</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Management</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>
     <para>
      Identifies channels the user may manage. To change these, select or
      deselect the appropriate check boxes and click the <guimenu>Update
      Permissions</guimenu> button. The permission to manage channels does
      not enable the user to create new channels. Note that channels
      automatically manageable through the user's admin status cannot be
      altered. These channels are identified with a check icon. Remember,
      &susemgr; administrators and channel administrators can subscribe
      to or manage any channel.
     </para>
    </sect4>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-usr-active-details-prefs">
    <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Preferences</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>
    <para>
     Configure the following settings for the user:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Email Notifications</guimenu>: Determine whether this user
       should receive email every time a patch alert is applicable to one or
       more systems in his or her &susemgr; account, as well as daily
       summaries of system events.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>&susemgr; List Page Size</guimenu>: Maximum number of
       items that appear in a list on a single page. If the list contains
       more items than can be displayed on one page, click the
       <guimenu>Next</guimenu> button to see the next page. This preference
       applies to the user's view of system lists, patch lists, package
       lists, and so on.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>Overview Start Page</guimenu>: Configure which information
       to be displayed on the <quote>Overview</quote> page at login.
      </para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       <guimenu>CSV Files</guimenu>: Select whether to use the default comma
       or a semicolon as separator in downloadable CSV files.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Change these options to fit your needs, then click the <guimenu>Save
     Preferences</guimenu> button. To change the time zone for this user,
     click on the <guimenu>Locale</guimenu> subtab and select from the
     drop-down menu. Dates and times, like system check-in times, will be
     displayed according to the selected time zone. Click <guimenu>Save
     Preferences</guimenu> for changes to take effect.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-usr-active-details-addresses">
    <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Addresses</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>
    <para>
     This tab lists mailing addresses associated with the user's account. If
     there is no address specified yet, click <guimenu>Add this
     address</guimenu> and fill out the form. When finished, click
     <guimenu>Update</guimenu>. To modify this information, click the
     <guimenu>Edit this address</guimenu> link, change the relevant
     information, and click the <guimenu>Update</guimenu> button.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-sm-user-details-notifs">
    <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Active</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Notification Methods</guimenu> — [Mon]</title>
    <para>
     This tab lists email addresses designated to receive alerts from
     monitoring probes. To set up alerts, click <guimenu>create new
     method</guimenu> and fill in the fields accordingly. To receive
     pager-style messages, select the associated <guimenu>Message
     Format</guimenu> check box to have the messages sent in a shorter
     format. When finished, click <guimenu>Create Method</guimenu>. The
     method shows up in the methods list, where it can be edited and
     deleted.
    </para>
    <para>
     If a notification method has probes attached, they are listed as well.
     If you are a monitoring administrator but don't have management rights
     for a system, its <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> and probe's
     <guimenu>Current State</guimenu> page are not accessible via links in
     their names. As always, &susemgr; administrators have full access to
     all aspects of your &susemgr; account.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-users-deactivated">
  <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>Deactivated</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>

  <para>
   The list of deactivated users also allows you to reactivate any of them.
   Click the check box to the left of their name and click the
   <guimenu>Reactivate</guimenu> button then the <guimenu>Confirm</guimenu>
   button. Reactivated users retain the permissions and system group
   associations they had when they were deactivated. Clicking a user name
   shows the <guimenu>User Details</guimenu> page.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-users-all">
  <title><guimenu>User List</guimenu> &gt; <guimenu>All</guimenu> — [Mgmt]</title>

  <para>
   The <guimenu>All</guimenu> page lists all users that belong to your
   organization. In addition to the fields listed in the previous two
   screens, the table of users includes a <guimenu>Status</guimenu> field.
   This field indicates whether the user is <guimenu>Active</guimenu> or
   <guimenu>Deactivated</guimenu>. Deactivated users are also grayed out to
   indicate their status. Click on the user name to see the <guimenu>User
   Details</guimenu> page.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
