<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- Converted by suse-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="s1-sm-actions">
<!--status="rfc"-->
 <title>Schedule</title>
 <info/>
<!--status="rfc"--><indexterm>
 <primary>Schedule</primary></indexterm><indexterm>
 <primary>WebLogic</primary>
 <secondary>Schedule</secondary></indexterm>
 <para>
  If you click the <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu> tab on the top navigation
  bar, the <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu> category and links appear. These
  pages enable you to track the actions carried out on your systems. An
  action is a scheduled task to be performed on one or more client systems.
  For example, an action can be scheduled to apply all patches to a system.
  Actions can also be grouped into action chains to schedule them at the
  same time in a particular order, for example to reboot a system after
  deploying patches.
 </para>
 <para>
  &susemgr; keeps track of the following action types:
 </para>
 <orderedlist spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    package alteration (installation, upgrade, and removal),
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    rollback package actions,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    system reboots,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    patch application,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    configuration file alteration (deploy, upload, and diff),
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    hardware profile updates,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    package list profile updates,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    automated installation initiation,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    service pack migrations,
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    remote commands.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>
 <para>
  Each page in the <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu> category represents an action
  status.
 </para>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-action-pend">
  <title>Pending Actions</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Pending Actions</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   As shown in <xref linkend="fig-schedule-fig"/>, the <guimenu>Pending
   Actions</guimenu> page appears by default when clicking
   <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu> in the top navigation bar. It displays
   actions not yet started or still in progress.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="fig-schedule-fig">
   <title>Schedule - Pending Actions</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="schedule.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="schedule.png" width="444"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-action-fail">
  <title>Failed Actions</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Failed Actions</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   Sometimes actions cannot be completed. If the action returns an error, it
   is displayed here.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-action-comp">
  <title>Completed Actions</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Completed Actions</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   List of actions successfully carried out.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-action-arch">
  <title>Archived Actions</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Archived Actions</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   If you selected actions to store for review, they are displayed here and
   can be deleted.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-action-chain">
  <title>Action Chains</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Action Chains</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   All created action chains are displayed here and can be deleted or
   modified by clicking on the chain name. In the top right corner is the
   <guimenu>delete action chain</guimenu> link. To add actions to the
   selected chain, choose from the links at the top, leading to various
   'chainable' actions: <guimenu>installing</guimenu> or
   <guimenu>upgrading</guimenu> packages, running a <guimenu>remote
   command</guimenu> and <guimenu>deploying a configuration file</guimenu>.
   Additionally, packages can be removed or verified, patches applied and
   systems rebooted via action chains.
  </para>

  <para>
   For all these operations, the action can either be scheduled for a
   certain date and time or added to an action chain. To create a new one,
   configure the first action (e.g. running a remote command), then select
   <guimenu>Add to Action Chain</guimenu> instead of <guimenu>Schedule no
   sooner than:</guimenu>. Click on the drop-down menu, enter a name, and
   click <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu> to save the chain. Then proceed to the
   next action and add it to the new chain.
  </para>

  <para>
   An action chain can be executed on all the systems it applies to. If more
   than one action applies to the same system, corresponding supported
   operations will be executed sequentially in action chain order. If a
   supported operation fails on a system, no further supported operations
   will be executed on that system.
  </para>

  <note>
   <para>
    &susemgr; does not enforce ordering across different systems.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   Action chains can be edited via the
   <menuchoice><guimenu>Schedule</guimenu><guimenu>Action
   Chains</guimenu></menuchoice> page. Click on a chain name to see the
   actions in the order they will be performed. The following tasks can be
   carried out here:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Changing the order by dragging the respective action to the right
     position and dropping it.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Deleting actions from the chain by clicking on the <guimenu>delete
     action</guimenu> link.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Inspecting the list of systems on which an action is run by clicking on
     the <guimenu>+</guimenu> sign.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Deleting a single system from an action by clicking on the
     <guimenu>delete system</guimenu> link.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Deleting the complete chain with the <guimenu>delete action
     chain</guimenu> link in the top-left corner.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Changing the action chain label by clicking on it.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Scheduling the action chain for execution after a certain date by
     clicking on the <guimenu>Save and Schedule</guimenu> button.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <note>
   <para>
    Note that if you leave the page without clicking on either
    <guimenu>Save</guimenu> or <guimenu>Save and Schedule</guimenu> all
    unsaved changes will be discarded. In this case, a confirmation dialog
    will pop up.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   Currently you cannot add an action to an action chain from the
   <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> page. Once a Chain is scheduled, the actions it
   contains will be displayed under <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu> on the
   appropriate pages: <guimenu>Pending Actions</guimenu>, <guimenu>Failed
   Actions</guimenu> or <guimenu>Completed Actions</guimenu>, depending on
   the status. If one action fails on a system no other actions from the
   same chain will be executed on that systems. Due to technical limitations
   it is not possible to reuse Action Chains
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <sect1 xml:id="s2-sm-action-list">
  <title>Actions List</title><indexterm>

  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>

  <secondary>Actions List</secondary></indexterm>

  <para>
   On each action page, each row in the list represents a single scheduled
   event or action that might affect multiple systems and involve various
   packages. The list contains several columns of information:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Filter by Action</guimenu> — Enter a term to filter the
     listed actions or use the check boxes in this column to select actions.
     Then either add them to your selection list or archive them by clicking
     <guimenu>Archive Actions</guimenu>. If you archive a pending action, it
     is not canceled, but the action item moves from the <guimenu>Pending
     Actions</guimenu> list to the <guimenu>Archived Actions</guimenu> list.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Action</guimenu> — Type of action to perform such as Patches
     or Package Install. Clicking an action name shows its <guimenu>Action
     Details</guimenu> page. Refer to <xref linkend="s3-sm-action-details"/>
     for more information.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Scheduled Time</guimenu> — The earliest day and time the
     action will be performed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Succeeded</guimenu> — Number of systems on which this action
     was successfully carried out.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Failed</guimenu> — Number of systems on which this action
     has been tried and failed.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>In Progress</guimenu> — Number of systems on which this
     action is taking place.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Total</guimenu> — Total number of systems on which this
     action has been scheduled.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <sect2 xml:id="s3-sm-action-details">
   <title>Action Details</title><indexterm>
   <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>
   <secondary>Action Details</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    If you click on the name of an action, the <guimenu>Action
    Details</guimenu> page appears. This page is split into the following
    tabs:
   </para>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-sm-action-details-details">
    <title><!-- <menuchoice><guimenu> -->
     Action Details &gt;
<!-- </guimenu> -->
<!-- <guimenu> -->
     Details
<!-- </guimenu></menuchoice> --></title>
    <para>
     General information about the action. This is the first tab you see
     when you click on an action. It displays the action type, scheduling
     administrator, earliest execution, and notes. Clicking the Patch
     Advisory takes you to the <guimenu>Patch Details</guimenu> page. The
     Patch Advisory appears only if the action is a patch. Refer to
     <xref linkend="s3-sm-errata-details"/> for more information.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-sm-action-details-completed">
    <title><!-- <menuchoice><guimenu> -->
     Action Details &gt;
<!-- </guimenu> -->
<!-- <guimenu> -->
     Completed Systems
<!-- </guimenu></menuchoice> --></title>
    <para>
     List of systems on which the action has been successfully performed.
     Clicking a system name displays its <guimenu>System Details</guimenu>
     page. Refer to <xref linkend="s3-sm-system-details"/> for more
     information.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-sm-action-details-progress">
    <title><!-- <menuchoice><guimenu> -->
     Action Details &gt;
<!-- </guimenu> -->
<!-- <guimenu> -->
     In Progress Systems
<!-- </guimenu></menuchoice> --></title>
    <para>
     List of systems on which the action is now being carried out. To cancel
     an action, select the system by marking the appropriate check box and
     click the <guimenu>Unschedule Action</guimenu> button. Clicking a
     system name shows its <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page. Refer to
     <xref linkend="s3-sm-system-details"/> for more information.
    </para>
   </sect3>
   <sect3 xml:id="s4-sm-action-details-failed">
    <title><!-- <menuchoice><guimenu> -->
     Action Details &gt;
<!-- </guimenu> -->
<!-- <guimenu> -->
     Failed Systems
<!-- </guimenu></menuchoice> --></title>
    <para>
     List of systems on which the action has failed. It can be rescheduled
     here. Clicking a system name takes you to its <guimenu>System
     Details</guimenu> page. Refer to <xref linkend="s3-sm-system-details"/>
     for more information.
    </para>
   </sect3>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
