<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:novdoc-profile.xsl" 
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC
  "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd"
[
  <!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
  %entities;
]>
<chapter id="s1-sm-your-rhn">
<!--status="rfc"-->

 <title>Overview</title><indexterm>

 <primary>Overview</primary>

 <secondary>Web interface</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>

 <primary>WebLogic</primary>

 <secondary>Overview</secondary></indexterm>

 <para>
  Entering the &susemgr; URL in a browser takes you to the
  <guimenu>Sign in</guimenu> screen. If you click on the <guimenu>About</guimenu> tab before logging in, you'll find documentation links, including a search function, and the option to request your login credentials if you forgot either password or login. Click on <guimenu>Lookup Login/Password</guimenu>.
 </para>
 <note id="s1-sm-forgot-creds">
 <para>
  If you forgot your password, enter your <guimenu>&susemgr;
  Login</guimenu> and <guimenu>Email Address</guimenu> in the
  <guimenu>Password Reset</guimenu> section and click the
  <guimenu>Send Password</guimenu> button. Your password will be reset
  and sent to you. If you cannot remember your username, enter your
  <guimenu>Email Address</guimenu> in the <guimenu>Login
  Information</guimenu> section, then click on <guimenu>Send
  Login</guimenu>. Your username will be sent to you.
 </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  After logging into the Web interface of &susemgr;, the first page to
  appear is <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>. This page contains important
  information about your systems, including summaries of system status,
  actions, and patch alerts.
 </para>

 <note>
  <para>
   If you are new to the &susemgr; Web interface, read
   <xref linkend="s1-sm-intro"/> to familiarize yourself with the layout and
   symbols used throughout the interface.
  </para>
 </note>

 <figure>
  <title>Overview</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata fileref="yourrhn.png" width="333"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata fileref="yourrhn.png" width="444"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>

 <para>
  This page is split into functional areas, with the most critical areas
  displayed first. Users can control which of the following areas are
  displayed by making selections on the
  <menuchoice><guimenu>Overview</guimenu><guimenu>Your
  Preferences</guimenu></menuchoice> page. Refer to
  <xref linkend="s2-sm-your-rhn-prefs"/> for more information.
 </para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Tasks</guimenu> area lists the most common tasks an
    administrator performs via the web. Click any link to reach the page
    within &susemgr; that allows you to accomplish that task.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If any systems have not been checking in to &susemgr;, they are listed
    under <guimenu>Inactive System</guimenu> to the right. Highlighting them
    in this way allows an administrator to quickly select those systems for
    troubleshooting.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Critical Probes</guimenu>[Mon] — Customers with monitoring enabled on their &susemgr; can also
    choose to include a list of all probes in the Critical state.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    <guimenu>Warning Probes</guimenu> [Mon] — Customers with monitoring enabled on their &susemgr; can also
    choose to include a list of all probes in the Warning state.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Most Critical Systems</guimenu> section lists the most
    critical systems within your organization. It provides a link to quickly
    view those systems and displays a summary of the patch updates that
    have yet to be applied to those systems. Click the name of the system to
    see its <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page and apply the patch
    updates.
<!-- ke, 2011-03-23: Never saw this 'out of date' page.
    But 'Systems' > 'Systems' features such a page.
    Now here we have 'View All Critical Systems'
-->
    Below the list is a link to <guimenu>View All Critical Systems</guimenu>
    on one page.
<!-- 'out of date' systems
    have applicable patch alerts that have not been applied.
-->
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Recently Scheduled Actions</guimenu> section lists all
    actions less than thirty days old and their status: failed, completed,
    or pending. Click the label of any given action to view its details
    page. Below the list is a link to <guimenu>View All Scheduled
    Actions</guimenu> on one page, which lists all actions that have not yet
    been carried out on your client systems.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Relevant Security Patches</guimenu> section lists all
    available security patches that have yet to be applied to some or all of
    your client systems. It is critical that you apply these security
    patches to keep your systems secure. Below this list find links to all
    patches (<guimenu>View All Patches</guimenu>) and to the patches that
    apply to your systems (<guimenu>View All Relevant Patches</guimenu>).
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>System Group Names</guimenu> section lists groups you may
    have created and indicates whether the systems in those groups are fully
    updated. Click the link below this section to get to the <guimenu>System
    Groups</guimenu> page, where you can choose <guimenu>System
    Groups</guimenu> to use with the System Set Manager.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Recently Registered Systems</guimenu> section lists the
    systems added to the &susemgr; in the past 30 days. Click a system's
    name to see its <guimenu>System Details</guimenu> page. Click the link
    below this section to <guimenu>View All Recently Registered
    Systems</guimenu> on one page.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <para>
  To return to this page, click <guimenu>Overview</guimenu> on the left
  navigation bar.
 </para>

 <sect1 id="s2-sm-your-rhn-account">
  <title>Your Account</title><indexterm>
  <primary>Oracle</primary>
  <secondary>Your Account</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>WebLogic</primary>
  <secondary>Your Account</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   On the <guimenu>Your Account</guimenu> page modify your personal
   information, such as name, password, and title. To modify any of this
   information, make the changes in the appropriate text fields and click
   the <guimenu>Update</guimenu> button in the bottom right-hand corner.
  </para>
  <para>
   If you change your &susemgr; password, for security reasons you
   will not see the new password while you enter it.
<!--This does not apply: Also for security, your password is represented
    by 12 asterisks no matter how many characters it actually contains.-->
   Replace the asterisks in the <guimenu>Password</guimenu> and
   <guimenu>Confirm Password</guimenu> text fields with the new password.
  </para>
  <note>
   <para>
    Should you forget your password or username, go to the login
    screen and click the <guimenu>About</guimenu> tab, then select
    the <guimenu>Lookup Login/Password</guimenu> page. Here you can
    either specify your login and email address or only your email
    address if you are not sure about the username. Then click on
    <guimenu>Send Password</guimenu> or <guimenu>Send Login</guimenu>
    respectively.
   </para>
  </note>
  <sect2 id="s3-sm-your-rhn-address">
   <title>Addresses</title><indexterm>
   <primary>account</primary>
   <secondary>change</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Oracle</primary>
   <secondary>Addresses</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    On the <guimenu>Addresses</guimenu> page manage your mailing, billing
    and shipping addresses, as well as the associated phone numbers. Just
    click <guimenu>Edit this address</guimenu> below the address to be
    modified, make the changes, and click <guimenu>Update</guimenu>.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="s3-sm-your-rhn-email">
   <title>Change Email</title><indexterm>
   <primary>email address</primary>
   <secondary>change</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Oracle</primary>
   <secondary>Email</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The email address listed in the <guimenu>Your Account</guimenu> page is
    the address to which &susemgr; sends email notifications if you select
    to receive patch alerts or daily summaries for your systems on the
    <guimenu>Your Preferences</guimenu> page.
   </para>
   <para>
    To change your preferred email address, click <guimenu>Change
    Email</guimenu> in the left navigation bar. Enter your new email address and click the
    <guimenu>Update</guimenu> button. A confirmation email is sent to the
    new email address; responding to the confirmation email validates the
    new email address. Invalid email addresses like those ending in
    <literal>@localhost</literal> are filtered and rejected.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="s3-sm-your-rhn-credentials">
   <title>Account Deactivation</title><indexterm>
   <primary>account</primary>
   <secondary>credentials</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    View or enter external system or API credentials associated with
    your SUSE Manager account, for example your &suse; Studio
    credentials.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="s3-sm-your-rhn-deactivate">
   <title>Account Deactivation</title><indexterm>
   <primary>account</primary>
   <secondary>deactivate</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
   <primary>Oracle</primary>
   <secondary>Account Deactivation</secondary></indexterm>
   <para>
    The <guimenu>Account Deactivation</guimenu> page provides a means to
    cancel your &susemgr; service. To do so, click the <guimenu>Deactivate
    Account</guimenu> button. The Web interface returns you to the login
    screen. If you attempt to log back in, an error message advises you to
    contact the &susemgr; administrator for your organization. Note that if
    you are the only &susemgr; Administrator for your organization, you are
    unable to deactivate your account.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="s2-sm-your-rhn-prefs">
  <title>Your Preferences</title><indexterm>
  <primary>Oracle</primary>
  <secondary>Your Preferences</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Your Preferences</guimenu> page allows you to configure
   &susemgr; options, including:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Email Notifications</guimenu> — Determine whether you want
     to receive email every time a patch alert is applicable to one or more
     systems in your account.
    </para>
    <important>
     <para>
      This setting also enables Management and Provisioning customers to
      receive a daily summary of system events. These include actions
      affecting packages, such as scheduled patches, system reboots, or
      failures to check in. In addition to selecting this check box, you must
      identify each system to be included in this summary email. By
      default, all Management and Provisioning systems are included in the
      summary. Add more systems either individually on the <guimenu>System
      Details</guimenu> page or for multiple systems at once in the
      <guimenu>System Set Manager</guimenu> interface. Note that &susemgr;
      sends these summaries only to verified email addresses. To disable
      all messages, simply deselect this check box.
     </para>
    </important>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>&susemgr; List Page Size</guimenu> — Maximum number of items
     that appear in a list on a single page. If more items are in the list,
     clicking the <guimenu>Next</guimenu> button displays the next group of
     items. This preference applies to system lists, patch lists, package
     lists, and so on.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>&quot;Overview&quot; Start Page</guimenu> — Select the
     information areas that are displayed on the <guimenu>Overview</guimenu>
     Start Page. Check the box to the left of the information area you would
     like to include.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>CSV Files</guimenu> — Select the separator character to be
     used in downloadable CSV files.  <guimenu>Comma</guimenu> is the
     default; as an alternative use <guimenu>Semicolon</guimenu>, which is
     more compatible with Microsoft Excel.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
   After making changes to any of these options, click the <guimenu>Save
   Preferences</guimenu> button.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="s2-yourrhn-locale">
  <title>Locale Preferences</title><indexterm>
  <primary>package installation</primary>
  <secondary>language</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>package installation</primary>
  <secondary>locale</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>WebLogic</primary>
  <secondary>language</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>WebLogic</primary>
  <secondary>locale</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   On the <menuchoice><guimenu>Overview</guimenu><guimenu>Locale
   Preferences</guimenu></menuchoice> page set your &susemgr; interface to
   your local time by selecting the appropriate <guimenu>Time Zone</guimenu>
   from the drop-down box, then click the <guimenu>Save
   Preferences</guimenu> button to apply the selection.
  </para>
<!-- FIXME: ATM, language selection is disabled
   <para>
    Select your preferred language. When the language preference is set
    to <guilabel>Use Browser Settings</guilabel>, &susemgr; uses the language
    preference from the user's browser (such
    as <application>Firefox</application>) to determine which language to use
    for the Web interface. When one of the listed languages is selected, the
    user sees the web interface in that language each time they log in,
    regardless of their browser's settings. Choosing a preferred language may
    be helpful for users traveling abroad. To select a default language, click
    the radio button to the left of the appropriate language and click
    the <guibutton>Save Preferences</guibutton> button to apply the change.
   </para>
  -->
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="s2-sm-systems-entitlements">
  <title>Subscription Management</title><indexterm>
  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>
  <secondary>entitling</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>&susemgr; Administrator</primary>
  <secondary>Entitlements</secondary></indexterm><indexterm>
  <primary>WebLogic</primary>
  <secondary>System Entitlements</secondary></indexterm>
  <para>
   To use all of the features of &susemgr;, your systems must be entitled
   — subscribed to &ncc;. Use the <guimenu>System Entitlements</guimenu>
   page to configure which systems are entitled to which service offerings.
  </para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 id="yourrhn-orgtrusts">
  <title>Organization Trusts</title>
  <para>
   The <guimenu>Organization Trusts</guimenu> page displays the trusts
   established with your organization (that is, the organization with which
   you, the logged-in user, are associated). The page also lists
   <guimenu>Channels Shared</guimenu>, which refers to channels available to your
   organization via others in the established trusts.
  </para>
  <para>
   You can filter the list of trusts by keyword using the <guimenu>Filter by
   Organization</guimenu> text box and clicking <guimenu>Go</guimenu>.
  </para>
  <para>
   For more information about organizational trusts, refer to
   <xref linkend="s1-sattools-orgs-trust"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
</chapter>
