<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook50-profile.xsl"
                 type="text/xml" 
                 title="Profiling step"?>

<!DOCTYPE chapter[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="white.papers.creating.custom.execution.modules">

    <title>Creating Custom Execution Modules</title>
    <para>The following chapter will guide you through the process of creating a custom execution
        module for use with Salt. Salt provides many execution modules out of the box that are used
        to wrap typical configuration tasks. You may wish to expand already existing Salt modules by
        creating a custom module designed around your configuration needs. Custom execution modules
        are written in python and may be added to your Salt configuration.</para>

    <warning>
        <title>White Papers</title>
        <para>All content contained in a White Papers document is under development and subject to change. Things will break
            and may not work as intended. For testing environments only. These documents are
            unsupported. </para>
    </warning>
    <sect1>
        <title>Creating an Execution Module for Snapper</title>
        <para>This exercise assumes you have already followed and created the master-less setup used
            in: <xref linkend="white.papers.writing.custom.salt.grains"/> You may use the same setup
            for the following exercise.</para>
        <note>
            <title>Testing Environment</title>
            <para>Ensure your test environment uses <filename>Btrfs</filename> as its filesystem and
                    <filename>Snapper</filename> is installed. (Snapper is installed by default on
                SUSE systems using Btrfs)</para>
        </note>

        <procedure>
            <title>Preparing the Snapper Module</title>
            <step>
                <para>Change the directories to:<filename>/srv/salt</filename>:</para>
                <screen># cd /srv/salt</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>To keep your Salt data organized, create a new <literal>_modules</literal>
                    directory. The _modules directory will contain any custom modules that will be
                    synced to minions:</para>
                <screen># md _modules</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Change to the new directory and create a new python file named
                        <literal>snapper.py</literal> containing the following content:</para>
                <screen>import dbus

bus = dbus.SystemBus()

snapper = dbus.Interface(bus.get_object('org.opensuse.Snapper',
                                       '/org/opensuse/Snapper'),
                         dbus_interface='org.opensuse.Snapper')


def list_snapshots(config='root'):

  '''
  List available snapshots
  '''
  return snapper.ListSnapshots(config)</screen>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Sync the New Module</title>
        <procedure>
            <title>Sync the New Snapper Module to Your Master-less Minion</title>
            <step>
                <para>In a normal Salt Master to minion setup you would target some or all of your
                    servers and run the <command>salt '*' saltutil.sync_all</command> command.
                    Alternatively you can narrow the scope to sync modules only using <command>salt
                        '*' saltutil.sync_modules</command>. Keep in mind this exercise is working
                    locally therefore you need to use the <command>salt-call</command> command
                    instead. Execute the following command to sync your new module with the
                    master-less minion now:</para>
                <screen>salt-call saltutil.sync_modules</screen>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Test the New Execution Module</title>
        <procedure>
            <title>Test your New Snapper Execution Module</title>
            <step>
                <para>If your python syntax is correct and you receive no errors the following call
                    should list all stored snapshots on your minion:</para>
                <screen>salt-call snapper.list_snapshots</screen>
                <note>
                    <title>Smoothing out the Data</title>
                    <para>This example is particularly short because the output from the D-Bus
                        Python bindings is in a format that can directly be serialized into the YAML
                        output you see on the command line. Normally you would rework/massage the
                        data and create a custom dictionary to return.</para>
                </note>
            </step>
        </procedure>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
        <title>Passing Values and Creating a New Function</title>
        <procedure>
            <title>Passing Values and Creating a New Snapper Function</title>
            <step>
                <para>In the previous steps you passed the name of a snapper configuration and gave
                    it a default configuration of <literal>def
                        list_snapshots(config='root')</literal>. Verify that you can pass other
                    configurations from the command line. The following command should throw an
                    error as this configuration does not exist:</para>
                <screen>salt-call snapper.list_snapshots config='test'</screen>
                <para>Revert the previous change to the default and the command should execute
                    properly as it is a valid snapper configuration:</para>
                <screen>salt-call snapper.list_snapshots config='root'</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Now you will add another function to
                        <filename>/srv/salt/_modules/snapper.py</filename> that allows you to
                    compare snapshots. Add the following definition to
                    <literal>snapper.py</literal>:</para>
                <screen>def compare(config='root', first=1, second=2):
  
  snapper.CreateComparison(config, first, second)
  
  return snapper.GetFiles(config, first, second)</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>After adding the new definition sync the module again:</para>
                <screen>salt-call saltutil.sync_modules</screen>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Now use the <command>list_snapshots</command> function to determine which
                    snapshots may be compared.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Try it out now by providing the snapshot IDs:</para>
                <screen>salt-call snapper.compare first=3 second=4</screen>
                <note>
                    <title>Listing Available Functions</title>
                    <para>Keep in mind you can always see what Salt module functions are available
                        by using the <command>salt-call sys.list_functions snapper</command>
                        command.</para>
                    <para>You can also list the complete set of documentation using the:
                            <command>salt-call sys.list_fucntions sys</command> command.</para>
                </note>
            </step>

        </procedure>

        <itemizedlist>
            <title>Final Recommendations</title>
            <listitem>
                <para>In production code you may want to add additional error handling and debugging
                    (e.g. logging).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Always add documentation to your modules. Remember that anything placed into
                    your functions <literal>docstrings</literal> is picked up by Salt’s
                    documentation framework automatically.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Before writing custom execution modules, check Salt documentation for existing
                    modules. <emphasis>There is already a far more powerful Snapper module that
                        exists external to this exercise.</emphasis></para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>



</chapter>
